<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons one on the subject of justification, the other on the imputed righteousness imputation of faith to righteousness, by which we are justified : preached occaisionally at the Merchants-Lecture in Pin-makers-Hall in Broad-street : and printed by their desire / by Walter Cross ...</title>
            <author>Cross, Walter, M.A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7266</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12900604</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12900604</idno>
            <idno type="VID">200303</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20887)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 200303)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 959:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons one on the subject of justification, the other on the imputed righteousness imputation of faith to righteousness, by which we are justified : preached occaisionally at the Merchants-Lecture in Pin-makers-Hall in Broad-street : and printed by their desire / by Walter Cross ...</title>
                  <author>Cross, Walter, M.A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by and for John Attwood ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans IV, 5 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Justification --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:200303:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:200303:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS. One on the Subject of Juſtification, The Other on The Imputed Righteouſneſs, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Faith to Righteouſneſs, by which we are Juſtified. Preached Occaſionally at the <hi>Merchants-Lecture</hi> in <hi>Pin-makers-Hall</hi> in <hi>Broad-ſtreet.</hi> And Printed at their Deſire. By <hi>Walter Croſs,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by and for <hi>John Aſtwood,</hi> at his Printing-Houſe behind St. <hi>Chriſtophers-Church</hi> in <hi>Thred-needle-ſtreet,</hi> the back-ſide of the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:200303:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:200303:2"/>
            <head>SERMON I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. IV. 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly —</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words are to be conſider'd both relatively and abſolutely, that we may in order comprehend their full ſenſe and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The relation they bear to the Apoſtle's ſcope and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, is that of a proof and confirmation of the grand Doctrine of the Goſpel, which is, <hi>That no man is, nor can be juſtified by his own Works or Righteouſneſs, the only way of being juſtified is by the Righteouſneſs of God.</hi> The Apoſtle on very good ground ſuppoſes ſuch an oppoſition and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction between them two as admits no medium, for we cannot be juſtified without a Righteouſneſs; and that Righteouſneſs muſt be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our own or anothers, God's or Man's. It is the Negative branch of the Doctrine the Apoſtle doth earneſtly contend for in this 4th. Chap. without any appearance of Carnality, but diſputes with ſtrenuous dint of Argument, and cloſely connected Topics with the terms of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Doctrine, whereof this in the Text is one; either an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Argument thus, <hi>He that worketh not, or is ungodly, cannot be juſtified by his own Works, but he who is juſtified by Grace is one that worketh not, or is ungodly,</hi> Erg. Or rather a Confirmation of an immediate Argument be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore brought, thus, Maj. <hi>He that is juſtifi'd by Faith, is not juſtifi'd by Works.</hi> Min. <hi>But</hi> Abraham <hi>was juſtified by Faith.</hi> Erg. Abraham <hi>was not juſtified by Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Aſſumption being confirm'd from Scriptures Teſtimony, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. he proceeds to prove the grand Propoſition thus, Maj. <hi>He to whom righteouſneſs is imputed of Grace, cannot be juſtified by Works.</hi> Min. <hi>But to him that is juſtified by Faith, righteouſneſs is imputed of Grace.</hi> Erg. <hi>He that is juſtified by Faith, cannot be juſtified by Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The aſſumption is frequently aſſerted in Scripture, <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>It is of Faith, that it might be by Grace.</hi> The grand Propoſition he ſuppoſes evident from the oppoſition between Grace and Debt in <hi>v.</hi> 4. for when a perſon is dealt with on the account of Works, <hi>i. e.</hi> any thing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:200303:3"/>in him, or done by him, it is debt, his due, I mean the reward; but when a Man is dealt with of Grace, the reward is proportion'd to the Favour and Good-will of the Donor or Judge; the Goodneſs of the Judge on the Bench, and the arraigned Perſon at the Bar, are very op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, therefore to be treated according to this oppoſite goodneſs, muſt be an oppoſite treatment.</p>
            <p>This oppoſition or repugnancy in <hi>v.</hi> 5. he illuſtrates and confirms thus, Maj. <hi>Where the ſubjects, cauſes, effects, or manner of efficiency, are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, there the things themſelves are oppoſite.</hi> Min. <hi>But in Juſtification by Works and Faith, of grace, and of due, the ſubjects, cauſes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are oppoſite.</hi> Erg. <hi>The Nature of the Juſtifications are oppoſite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The grand Propoſition is a Maxim in Logic, or Natural Light, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for granted. The aſſumption is illuſtrated and confirmed in theſe four <hi>Verſes.</hi> 1. The Subjects, to wit, a godly and an ungodly Man, a righteous and an unrighteous, a Worker and a Non-worker. 2. The Cauſes, the grace, favour and good-will of the Governour, and the merit, labour, obedience and righteouſneſs of the Subject. 3. The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate effect of this Free-grace, or way of its efficiency, which differs from the Method of Juſtice, meaſuring its diſtribution by Law; for the former imputes a Righteouſneſs, or as in <hi>Ch.</hi> 5. gives a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> in a way of accompt and reckoning, that by virtue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and its ſatisfaction to the Government, it may conſiſt with govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing goodneſs to bleſs <hi>the bleſſedneſs of the man unto whom God imputes righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs without works.</hi> The latter finds an inherent righteouſneſs in the perſon, and therefore his Juſtification is only an Authoritative de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of what he is, a ſurrender of the Honour that is his due; and he proves this by <hi>David</hi>'s Teſtimony, aſſerting the former Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be a Pardon or Forgiveneſs: As if he had ſaid, It's call'd a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, becauſe that Pardon is the effect of an Imputed Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Free-grace firſt gives by way of Account an Intereſt in Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and conveys the Right or Intereſt thorough Faith. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Pardons on the account of that Righteouſneſs, which gives juſt ground for the denomination of Juſtification, and this Name is entertain'd as the proper Name for our Pardon in the Goſpel, that it may be a conſtant Memorial of our Obligation to Chriſt for our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and of the difficulty that there was to render a Pardon conſiſtent with the Law and Honour of the Law-maker and Governour. One chief end of this added Teſtimony of <hi>David</hi>'s to the Example and Pattern of <hi>Abraham,</hi> is to prove that we are not juſtified by Works, from the Nature of Goſpel-Juſtification, <hi>viz. David</hi> ſays it's a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; tho' it's a Juſtification in reſpect to Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, it's
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:200303:3"/>a Forgiveneſs with reſpect to our own Unrighteouſneſs. This proves the Subject alſo of Goſpel Juſtification to be ungodly, for we need and receive a Pardon, not as righteous or godly, but ungodly: And the reaſon why the Apoſtle gives the ſenſe of <hi>David</hi>'s words to be the Imputing of a Righteouſneſs, is becauſe it was inconſiſtent with a neceſſary juſt Law, and a juſt Governour and Judge, who cannot do violence to a righteous Law, to pardon or not to impute ſin, until there be firſt a Righteouſneſs imputed; and by ſhowing this to be the ſenſe of it, he thereby proves that our Juſtification is of Grace, becauſe Free grace is the only cauſe of the Imputation of that Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs. It is not for Chriſt's ſake that his righteouſneſs is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for that were to ſay, that the ſame thing was for the ſake of it ſelf, his Merit for his Merits-ſake, and Righteouſneſs for his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs-ſake: But as Chriſt is the Free-grace of God's Gift, ſo is his Righteouſneſs, without any interveening Merits; and that has made me think, the influence of Chriſt's Merit, to uſe the accuſtom'd Phraſe, terminates on the Law, or Legal conſtitution, not on the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. God is the God, Author and Owner of all Grace, nothing has chang'd his mind into a more gracious temper, and hence the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of righteouſneſs is only aſcrib'd to Grace, but Juſtification is aſcrib'd to Grace, not immediately as imputation is, but at ſecond hand: <hi>Juſtified by his Grace thorough the Redemption,</hi> Ch. 3.24. Hence ſomething may be ſaid for an Imputation of Righteouſneſs from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, tho' not for Juſtification from Eternity; and may be this is the reaſon why another Phraſe is made uſe of for the tranſitory, tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Act, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith imputed to righteouſneſs; for that denotes God's Act as Judge, in paſſing the abſolving Sentence, <hi>i. e.</hi> thorough the Gift of Faith he conveys a right to that Righteouſneſs, which from Eternity was aſſign'd in the Book of Life to all that ſhall ever enjoy its bleſſed Fruits. Thus much for the coherent and relative ſenſe of the words, as they are ſubſervient and uſeful to prove that we are not juſtified by Works.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now conſider them abſolutely: And I muſt ſay this of them ſo conſidered, that they are as pure Goſpel-Language-Expreſſions, as full of encouragement to Sinners, and comfort to Penitents, as any I know in Scripture. Indeed they are not alone, for the ſame Apoſtle ſays Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically of himſelf, what he aſſerts elenctically here of Free-grace, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>viz.</hi> That he was a <hi>Blaſphemer,</hi> a <hi>Perſecutor,</hi> and <hi>injurious Perſon,</hi> when abundant grace, together with Faith and Love pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented him, <hi>i. e.</hi> juſtifying and ſanctifying grace; the one in Faith and Love, the other in the abundant grace conveyed thorough them;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:200303:4"/>and <hi>v.</hi> 16. he ſhows, this was no ſingular favour, for Chriſt made a <hi>pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of him to them who ſhould hereafter believe;</hi> as Artiſts hang out a piece of their Workmanſhip to bring in Cuſtomers, ſo Chriſt hangs up <hi>Paul</hi> for a ſign, that all who hear the Goſpel may count Chriſt (who came to ſave ſinners) worthy of Acceptation, by all who are ſinners. The Language of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Converſion is the ſame with that of his Doctrine: Grace finds us ſinners, and makes us righteous, and then bleſſed. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is <hi>Paul</hi> the only Pattern; <hi>Levi</hi> is another, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.14. Sitting at the receipt of Cuſtom, ſerving a Tyrannical Government in its heavy Taxes; Chriſt calls him powerfully and effectually into the ſervice and glory of his Kingdom, and makes an Offer to the reſt of the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Sinners; <hi>That he came not to call the righteous,</hi> (who did repent) <hi>but ſinners to repentance:</hi> His Office was to be a Phyſitian to the ſick: And <hi>Zacheus</hi> a chief Commiſſioner is a third, who by falſe Methods had aggravated the Burthen of Tribute, and robb'd honeſt ſubjects, under the Notion of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s due; yet Chriſt tells him, ſalvation is come to his houſe: For that was his conſtant Employ, <hi>To ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt:</hi> But here we have it doctrinally, what is there hiſtorically, here univerſally aſſerted, what is there illuſtrated by Examples and Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; here in ſtrict Logical Terms, what is there under Rhetorical Flouriſhes, that when a man is ungodly and without works, then Faith is imputed for righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> I ſhall divide them in theſe two parts: 1ſt. As they ſet forth the condition of a ſinner, antecedent to juſtification. 2ly. In what me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod God brings them from that condition into bleſſedneſs through <hi>an Imputation of Righteouſneſs, and imputation of Faith to Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt Part affords us this Doctrine.</p>
            <q>Doct. <hi>That the Object of Juſtification, antecedently to it, is a perſon without works of righteouſneſs, an ungodly man.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>When in our blood he bids us live, the day of our Enmity was the time of his Love, the Condition of our Adamical Nakedneſs was that he caſt the skirt of his beautiful Garments over; when aliens, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd into a Covenant of Grace with us, order'd for the ſalvation of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; when in our filthineſs, he puts his Comelineſs on us, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. The plain Goſpel ſence of theſe Prophetical Figures is, <hi>To him that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, but believeth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are three Limitations put on this Text, by Inteepreters of differing Opinions, from what is the old and common road of them call'd Proteſtants, who uſually diſtinguiſh the caſe thus, as <hi>Altingius</hi> conſider'd
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:200303:4"/>in himſelf, he is ungodly and unrighteous, but conſidered in Chriſt he is righteous; or Dr. <hi>Tuckney,</hi> finds him unrighteous, but leaves him not ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some diſtinguiſh as to time thus, was ungodly, not is; they rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon ſome little time before for the exerciſe of Faith and Repentance, before he can be juſtifi'd. A Priority of Order between the Gift of Faith and Juſtification I willingly grant, but a priority of time is pregnant with Abſurdities: The former doth not ſerve their turn, who make the Exerciſe of faith and repentance Conditions of juſtification; for it requires no time; as the Sun is in no time before its Beams, nor the Ring before the relation of Man and Wife: Relations reſult immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from their foundations, but the mind of Man, tho' it needs leſs time for the nimble ſucceſion of its ſwift thoughts, yet time it doth require. (2.) Man muſt be regenerate, effectually call'd, before faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, for the tree muſt be good before the fruit: Now its repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to think one regenerate, a ſon of God, can be in a ſtate of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and it's as inconſiſtent, to think that any are out of a ſtate of Condemnation before a pardon. But to ſuppoſe any time between re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation and forgiveneſs, for the exerciſe of faith and repentance, is to ſuppoſe a time when we are neither in a ſtate of Condemnation or Juſtification. (3.) <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt:</hi> Now we are united to Chriſt by a double Cement, the Spirit working faith, and faith therefore where that Cement is there is no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but pardon. (4.) The Scripture ſays, <hi>We were reconciled when ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> Rom. 5.10. The difficulty here is, if this be meant the price for peace paid, or the application of it in juſtification, <hi>v.</hi> 9. ſhows the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; being now juſtifi'd by his blood, either we are juſtifi'd at Chriſt's death, which the party denies, or elſe we are enemies when juſtifi'd; and indeed reconciliation ſignifies a mutual peace, the hatred remov'd on on ſide by pardon, and on the other by regeneration; a new temper of Mind. It is true. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. it is ſaid, <hi>Who ſometime were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but now are reconcil'd;</hi> yet that ſuppoſes the ſame time to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue until the reconciliation, which <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. ſays was the time of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. A (5th.) Argument is from the oneneſs of time, by Scripture Connexion between regeneration and juſtification, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13. <hi>You hath he quicken'd, together with him, having forgiven you all treſpaſſes,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.3. <hi>We are call'd to glory and vertue at once, and</hi> 1 Pet. 1.3. <hi>are begotten again unto an inheritance incorruptible,</hi> Tit. 3.5, 7. 2 Cor. 6. <hi>ult.</hi> A (6th.) Argument is from <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. Where the Apoſtles ſolution to the objection of <hi>Libertines,</hi> is, from the near connection between juſtifying and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying grace. (7.) I ſee nothing in the context to favour this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but <hi>é contra</hi> would overturn the Arguments and Doctrine too.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:200303:5"/>
            <p>A 2d. <hi>Limitation</hi> is, from diſtinction of Laws; they own he is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly man, a Non worker, as to the righteouſneſs of the Law, ſtrictly ſo call'd, (which requires perfect, perpetual and perſonal obedience) who is the Object of Evangelical Juſtification. But they think there is a neceſſity of a righteouſneſs to another, new, diſtinct Law; for as Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Juſtification requires Legal Righteouſneſs, Evangelical Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on requires Evangelical Righteouſneſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> Faith and Repentance, in ſincerity and perſeverance: And this laſt qualification comes in, leaſt they ſhould be under a neceſſity to hold a man pardon'd one time of his Life, and yet be afterward condemn'd thorough after back-ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and falling from Grace. Some of them hold final falling away, and ſo an once juſtifi'd man may be eternally damn'd: Others total, but not final, and ſo may be in a ſtate of Condemnation and Juſtification al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatively a hundred times: But a third, to prevent this Abſurdity, adds perſeverance, by which a man is excluded from juſtification until his laſt breath, which excludes the Doctrine of Aſſurance during life, and pardon too, which is a ſtrangely new Doctrine; yet I have heard ſome more cautious perſons ſay, they think there are ſome degrees of Grace, at the attainment of which they eſcape that danger; may be that is it they allot for the time of juſtification. This Limitation ſeems unaccep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to me on theſe grounds,</p>
            <p n="1">1. This Law countenances iniquity, indulges tranſgreſſions; for ſince the firſt Law is holy, juſt and good, what Law requires leſs, is ſo far unholy, unjuſt, bad; and ſhall we ſuppoſe an holy God, that is of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer eyes than to connive at iniquity, to eſtabliſh iniquity by a Law? was our corrupt natures, or imperfectly renew'd to his image, the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal to this Law? as his own Nature gave birth to the firſt, it ſeems reaſonable to ſay that God accepts imperfect obedience on his account who perform'd perfect obedience in our ſtead as ſurety; but that the office of the Mediator ſhould be to obtain of God to lay by that glorious manifeſtation of his Holineſs, and change that perfect Law into a Council and Directory, and to yield ſo far to us, as to take a penny of the pound of obedience from broken debtors, ſeems to me pregnant of difficulties and abſurdities. We deny our Obedience comes to be accepted as the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the Law requires, or under the Notion <hi>Adam</hi>'s righteouſneſs was accepted, <hi>viz.</hi> that which gave right to Indemnity and Life, but is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as the way to the Kingdom, and preparation for the poſſeſſion of a place in theſe manſions, where all the inhabitants are holy: It is the righteouſneſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt alone, by which that Law is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill'd; he is the end of the Law for righteouſneſs, and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs gives right to remiſſion and bleſſedneſs.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:200303:5"/>
            <p n="2">2ly. I am inform'd, this Notion of the Evangelical Law was the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal error of the <hi>Antinomians;</hi> for they ſaid, ſince Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance was all that was neceſſary to ſalvation, what was the need of any other Law? Alas, it is a ſad miſtake; for the Moral Law is the rule of true Repentance: <hi>Let him that ſtole, ſteal no more;</hi> that hath broke the firſt, ſecond, or third Command, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ought to do ſo no more; that is true Repentance, New Obedience: The Law that did forbid ſtealing once, forbids ſtealing always, elſe it were not perfect. Indeed the Goſpel has ſuch an influence on this Law, and our obedience to it, that it is a new Law to what it was; but that ever God ſhould lay that by, and make another, or make any that requires not perfection, is to me unconceivable: If any duty belongs to this New Law, it's patience, and God commands that it be perfect; <hi>Let patience have its perfect work:</hi> Or, for the ſame God to have two Laws, ſo contrary, that we may condemn'd by one, and juſtifi'd by another.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. As it introduces <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> ſo a chriſtianiz'd <hi>Phariſaiſm,</hi> which was the error the Apoſtle is refuting: He is not diſputing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Pagans,</hi> who denied the Meſſias, or own'd many Daemons, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>To us there is but one God the Father, of whom are all things, and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom are all things:</hi> Nor againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd he was come in the fleſh; for he tells them, their Faith was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous thorough the World, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8. But againſt ſome that believ'd, and pleaded the neceſſity of Circumciſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. That pleaded, <hi>We were juſtified by Faith and Works;</hi> for the Theſis, ſhows the Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts Opinion, which is, we are <hi>juſtifi'd by faith, without the deeds of the Law,</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23. They ſought after a righteouſneſs, <hi>as if it were by the works of the Law,</hi> i. e. by the works of the Law in ſome ſenſe and meaſure; this may be more evident by conſidering the <hi>Jews</hi> Doctrine about the way of Salvation, and add to it the belief of a Meſſias come, and we may find the opinions too much alike: They reckon'd that there were three ranks of Men, with reſpect to Heaven; the loweſt were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; of Publicans and Sinners we read frequently; the higheſt were perfect men, and that they thought hardly attainable it ſeems, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21. That was the young mans doubt he brought to Chriſt; <hi>If thou wouldſt be perfect, ſell all thou haſt, and follow me;</hi> in me the Laws perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to be obtain'd, thou muſt entirely be deny'd to all things elſe; the middle ſort was called <hi>Beninim,</hi> Middle-way-men, Men of ſincerity, that ſhould go to eternal Life, either by a praeponderation of good, or repentance of evil: <q rend="inline">Hence, ſay they, the Life of man in the Precepts is according to his intention, who performs one of the leaſt Precepts, for love of the Precept, ſhall merit everlaſting life, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Open to me,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:200303:6"/>my Siſter, my Love;</hi> i. e. Open to me one crevice of Repentance, and I will open to thee the wide gates of Glory, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.1. The Land of <hi>Hadrach,</hi> i. e. <hi>Emanuel</hi>'s Land, who leads men to God by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the way of repentance. The gates of Prayer are ſhut ſometimes, but never the gate of Repentance: If <hi>Iſrael</hi> would repent one day, the world would be redeem'd, and the Meſſias would come.</q> But they did not think theſe <hi>Boninim</hi> went ſtraight to Heaven; No, <hi>Abraham,</hi> and all the Prophets went to Hell in their Opinion; though the beſt went thorough the fire like a <hi>Salamander,</hi> it's only the Meſſias can deliver from that. Herein then ſeems their Error to conſiſt, that the Meſſias ſuppli'd the want of perfection, ſo no need of going to Hell for ſincere ones; this the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. calls a perverting of the Goſpel, a compoſing of another method of Salvation, a counterfeit Goſpel, a corrupting of the pure method of Grace with mixture and allay of works.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. It ſuppoſes two Juſtifications, <hi>Baxter</hi> againſt <hi>Cartwright,</hi> p. 11. <q rend="inline">It is one thing to be accus'd of treaſon, and another thing to be accus'd of Non-performance of the condition on which remiſſion for treaſon is promis'd; an abſolution from the firſt makes the one juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and abſolution, from the latter the Goſpel Juſtification.</q> 
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> By this Doctrine the neglect of Faith and Repentance is not Treaſon. 2. That the juſtification by Chriſts righteouſneſs is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. 3. That we muſt be juſtifi'd, before we can have an intereſt in Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and ſo we have Faith and Repentance without an intereſt in Chriſt, for antecedent to an intereſt in him; and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be evangelically juſtifi'd until our Faith and Repentance be ſincere, and perſevere, ſo no intereſt in him till death. The Scholaſtick <hi>Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arne,</hi> Provoſt of the Old Colledge of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> weeps over this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and its Reverend Author, thus, <hi>p.</hi> 285. <q rend="inline">O Reverend <hi>Baxter,</hi> for what end, or to what good haſt thou wrote ſo many Volumes, for thy conditional juſtification by Faith and Obedience? to how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny contentions haſt thou given occaſion? how many precious hours haſt thou loſt to thy ſelf and thy Reverend Brethren? into an Abyſs of how many Anti-Goſpel Errors are they now ſunk, who glory in thee as their Guide and Patron? who after they have once left the way of Truth, ſcarce know where to ſtop, and yet thou ſtill telleſt the world, all thy diſputes are about the wool of a dog, for thou diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt only in words and names from thy Brethren.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5ly. The Context and Scope is the beſt rule of interpreting this text, whether righteous by one Law, and unrighteous by another, or not; for <hi>Chapter</hi> 3. tells us, he is a Non-worker as to all works, that any Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Old Teſtament did diſcover to be duty; for <hi>v.</hi> 2. this was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:200303:6"/>the <hi>Jews</hi> advantage, that unto them were committed the Oracles of God, about which theſe two things are certain, that theſe Oracles were the Old Teſtament, and that the Old Teſtament contain'd the ſame way of juſtification the New doth; <hi>v.</hi> 19. He adds, <hi>whatever the Law ſays, it ſays to them that are under the Law:</hi> v. 10. Theſe Oracles ſay, <hi>There is none righteous, No, not one:</hi> v. 19. <hi>All the World is guilty, before God every mouth ſtopp'd:</hi> The Argument runs thus, The Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment contain'd all Laws, wherein a ſinners juſtification was concern'd; but as to all theſe Laws, all men were found Non-workers, and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, therefore there is no place for diſtinction of Laws and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this place, that inheres in us. 2ly. <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Condition, antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to his effectual call, inſtructs us, that the diſtinction of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be admitted in this place, is that of our own and anothers, made ours by imputation; not of our own, with reſpect to different Laws; for <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24. <hi>Abraham</hi> was an idolater, inconſiſtent with faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, or Goſpel-righteouſneſs, and yet <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41. He is call'd a <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man,</hi> and <hi>the friend of God;</hi> this muſt be thorough Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs imputed, not his own: <hi>Who call'd the righteous man from the eaſt,</hi> he was righteous in <hi>Chaldea.</hi> 3ly. Rom. 5.9, 10. <hi>When we were enemies, we were reconcil'd to God by the death of his Son:</hi> The Argument is thus, If we are reconcil'd when enemies, we are juſtifi'd when guilty, I mean actively and antecedently; but the Apoſtle affirms the former: The Connexion is evident, for they are but different Metaphors of the ſame caſe, the one repreſenting it as the happy concluſion of a fair Tryal at Law, the other as a Quarrel more friendly and privately compos'd; the one repreſents it as a publick crime pardon'd, on a ſatisfaction and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation, the other as a miſunderſtanding, made up by an arbitration; the one expreſſes the remiſſion of the guilt, but the other the removal of enmity, to a cordial renew'd Peace and Love on both ſides. Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation comprehends Juſtification and Sanctification too; <hi>Two cannot walk together, except they be agreed.</hi> This is further confirm'd from <hi>v.</hi> 9. where by Reconciliation is underſtood and expreſs'd Juſtification, the former is deſcrib'd by the latter, and this juſtification, <hi>v.</hi> 1. ſaid to be that which is by faith. Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> to ſhun the dint of this Argument, grants in this place a juſtification on Chriſt's Death, but <hi>v.</hi> 8, and 9. the one is diſtinguiſh'd from the other by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>yet</hi> and <hi>now, i. e.</hi> Then he dy'd for us, now we are juſtifi'd. 4ly. We may take one ſtep further into the Context, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1, 2, 6, 7. where the Apoſtle propoſes an apparent Objection, but impertinent, if that were the caſe, no juſtification until ſincerity, and perſeverance in faith and repentance: <hi>Shall we continue in ſin, that grace may abound?</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:200303:7"/>if their Mind and the Apoſtle's had been one, he had anſwer'd like them, tho' Legal Obedience is not neceſſary to <hi>make</hi> us veſſels of Grace, Goſpel Righteouſneſs is; but his Solution is founded on the neceſſary connexion between juſtifying and ſanctifying grace, being given at once both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: <hi>How ſhall we that are dead to ſin live any longer therein,</hi> v. 2. This ſuppoſes a mortal ſtroke given to the body of ſin in the ungodly man when juſtified, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>He that is dead is juſtifi'd from ſin;</hi> ſo is the word in the Original; and <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>They that are in Chriſt Jeſus, have crucifi'd the fleſh with its affections and luſts.</hi> Thus Dr. <hi>Tuckney,</hi> God's juſtifying act finds us ungodly, but doth not leave us ſo; he juſtifies the ungodly, but the ungodly are not juſtified; and this obviates an Argument that is brought out of the text to confirm this Opinion; for, ſay they, how can he be ungodly that has faith? its true, he cannot, but Faith may be given to him that is ſo.</p>
            <p>The 3d. <hi>Objection</hi> is this, he may be a Non-worker as to true graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous works, the effects of a regenerate ſtate, but not a Non-worker as to preparatory works, that may make us meet and fit for it: Or, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the old terms, without meriting works, but not congruous works. It is neceſſary to give ſome Characters of theſe, before any thing be ſaid againſt them, or rather againſt their neceſſary anteceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to juſtification; for I doubt not, pardoning grace finds many ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued. The Original of theſe works is ſuppos'd to be man's natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, excited by ſome common influence of the Spirit, and may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken'd by ſome extrordinary or afflicting providence, or ſome convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing truth. 2. The Properties of the Works are three, (1.) Good for matter and end. (2.) Done freely. (3.) When we are in the way for convictions, or ſorrow in Hell, are not preparatory works. 3. The degrees they differ in from gracious or meriting works are two, (1.) The perſon is not in a ſtate of Grace. (2.) God has made no promiſe that he will pardon or juſtifie ſuch; thus Bp. <hi>Abelly, edit</hi> 11. <hi>Medulla Theol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1. Theſe Characters make theſe Works more a counterfeit of Grace than preparation for Grace, they deſcribe a Phariſee or Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, that is further from the kingdom of Heaven than a Publican or Harlot; for, Chriſt tells them, the harlots went into the kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven before them; the Publican went home rather juſtified than the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee, with his formal thanks to God for his diſtinguiſhing Godneſs: Moſt of ſuch deceive themſelves with that vain ſhew of Godlineſs, having a form of Godlineſs, but denying the power thereof; when they are poor, miſerable, wretched and naked, they think they need nothing, with the lukewarm Church of <hi>Laodicea:</hi> Theſe are the fooliſh Virgins that have no Oil in their Lamps.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:200303:7"/>
            <p n="2">2ly. The foundations this Opinion are grounded on, are not very ſure: As, 1. They ſay <hi>John Baptiſt's</hi> Miniſtry was to prepare the way to Chriſt, by the doctrine of Repentance. <hi>Reſpon.</hi> The <hi>Baptiſts</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry is to be conſider'd either in general, with all Miniſters, to prepare and make meet for the inheritance, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.6. <hi>To prepare his ways, to give knowledge of Salvation unto his people, by the remiſſion of their ſins, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the tender mercies of our God:</hi> His Work was to fit for Heaven, not to make Hypocrites, though he did make many. 2. His Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry was to be conſider'd, in relation to that peculiar diſpenſation which was to raiſe and awaken peoples minds, in expectation of the Meſſias, and fulfilment of the great promiſes about the incarnation of the Son of God, his Birth, Life, Death, Reſurrection and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Church, which was peculiar to himſelf.</p>
            <p>A Second Foundation of theſe preparatory Works is Chriſt's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, preferring one People to another as ſuch, with whom the means that others enjoy'd in vain, would have prevail'd for their true Repentance, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. to this purpoſe Chriſt prefers the <hi>Tyrians</hi> and <hi>Sidonians</hi> to the People of <hi>Chorazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida.</hi> For Anſwer, I ſhall give <hi>Camero</hi>'s Senſe of theſe Expreſſions, who counts it a popular Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbole to upbraid the Unbelief of theſe People, who had ſeen ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Miracles; as if one ſhould ſay, he is as bad or worſe than the Devil, and theſe things ſeem to confirm this ſenſe. 1. It would ſeem to reflect on the Bowels and Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that he would not walk two or three Miles to work a Miracle, among a People who wanted nothing elſe to ſecure their Salvation, and yet continue to Preach and work Miracles, where he knew the event would be only the Aggravation of their Sin and Puniſhment. 2. To attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the Converſion of a People to any external means, and not the efficacy and energy of the Holy Ghoſt, is contrary to the ſenſe of the Holy Ghoſt, for <hi>Paul may plant, and Apollo may water, but God gives the encreaſe;</hi> and yet theſe words taken litterally would imply this, if in <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> the Miracles had been done, which have been done in thee, they would have repented long ago. 3. The Letter of this Scripture would arrogate the power of Converſion to Miracles, which certainly is not the Senſe of the Scripture, for <hi>Abram</hi> in the 16th. of <hi>Luke</hi> is brought in, ſaying in that Conference with the rich man, <hi>that if they heard not Moſes and the Prophets, they would not believe one that roſe from the dead.</hi> 4. Such Hyperbolical Language Chriſt frequently us'd, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.8, 9. If thy Hand or thy Foot offend thee, cut it off; if any man ſmite thee on the right Cheek, turn to him the other; when thou doſt Alms, let not thy left hand know what thy right hand doth:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:200303:8"/>And of this kind ſeems <hi>Moſes</hi> his Wiſh to be, who pray'd that God would rather blot him out of the Book of Life, than deſtroy that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: The import of it, was only to expreſs the earneſtneſs of his deſire.</p>
            <p>A Third Foundation is Chriſt's commendation of the young Man, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.15. <hi>Mark</hi> 10.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.18. where 'tis ſaid, Jeſus lov'd him, and that he lack'd but one thing of the Kingdom of Heaven. <hi>Reſp.</hi> (1.) The ſame Scripture gives no account of his coming there, but rather of the impoſſibility of it, and that 'twas eaſier for a Camel to go through the Eye of a Needle, than for ſuch a Man to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven; and farther, that 'twas a thing only poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God: And in more plain terms, he deſcribes him to be one who truſted in his riches, and what can more unfit Man for Heaven? God and Mammon are at greateſt diſtance. As to that Expreſſion of his loving him, I think it may be beſt explain'd by that diſtinction that is us'd about Chriſt's Tears, when he wept over a dead <hi>Lazarus,</hi> or ſympathiz'd with his Siſters, that they were expreſſions of his Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and that tho' he had not the like Paſſions, yet the like Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with us, and could love what's uſeful and in its kind beautiful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, and ſuch are all theſe Moral Virtues, that renders a Man amiable and uſeful in the Society where he lives.</p>
            <p>A Fourth Foundation is, that an Appetite and deſire is antecedent unto enjoying Chriſt or his Benefits, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Ho every one that thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, come ye to the Waters. Reſp.</hi> That is every one; there is a great difference between a deſire, and the determination of it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſay, <hi>i. e.</hi> all, or all unconverted, <hi>Who will ſhew us any good? but, Lord, lift thou up on me the light of thy countenance:</hi> It is the termination of their deſires on Chriſt, on ſtable, laſting, heavenly, ſpiritual good things the Prophet exhorts to, he blames them for terminating their deſires on what did not profit. A (3.) Argument againſt preparato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Works ſeems to be their inconſiſtence with the Nature of Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for Creation, Regeneration, Reſurrection and Victory, have no antecedent prediſpoſitions; all the preparation in order to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd and overcome, is to oppoſe with the greater force to prevent it; the others imply a Divine Omnipotency, working upon nothing, or what's unfit for the produc'd effect. (4.) It being granted that there's no neceſſary Connection between preparatory Works and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, I ſee no reaſon why ſome may not be pardon'd without it, as well as ſome have it, and not pardoned. (5.) The deſign of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel being to exalt pardoning Grace, <hi>Ver.</hi> 15, 16. <hi>It's of Faith, that it might be of Grace:</hi> The leſs the Preparation appear, the more Grace is exalted and manifeſted.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:200303:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Should then a Man do nothing until he be juſtified? <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are juſtified who know it not. 2. Our Priviledges are not the Rule of our Duty, but God's Command. 3. That is, without doubt, we ſhould do all we can, few if any do what they may, be always trying whether God gives ability or not. 4. To all under the means of Grace, at leaſt God gives common Grace, and by that they may live a ſober, juſt and honeſt Life among men, and they may and ought to attend on Ordinances, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Work in and about your own Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as <hi>Camero</hi> excellently tranſlates it, wait there until God works effectually, he doth it of his own good pleaſure, where and when he will. Let fear and trembling therefore accompany thy attendance, leſt thou miſs the gale of that Wind that blows where it liſteth: Here is no room for Idleneſs to a Non converted and unpardoned Soul: <hi>Faith comes by hearing,</hi> be thou a diligent hearer. 5. God gives Life thorough the Command of the Law, he ſpeaks a Pardon thorough the Precept; it's that makes the Law evangelical, when he commands the dead to ariſe; <hi>Lazarus, come forth;</hi> Lame Cripple, riſe and walk; Bed rid man, carry home thy bed, thy ſins are forgiven thee.</p>
            <p>Having removed theſe Limitations, with the grounds of them, I ſhall eſtabliſh the Doctrine more poſitively: And, (1.) By Teſtimony: <hi>Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> on this Verſe reconciles it with <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.15. where it's ſaid, <hi>He that juſtifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the juſt, even they both are abomination to the Lord:</hi> It were an abomination to juſtifie a wicked Man, without a ſatisfaction, but not where a ſatisfaction to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is given, which is the Caſe of the ungodly Man in the Text. <hi>Who's juſtified thro' the righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> and this he quotes out of <hi>Pareus</hi> on the place: <hi>Wilſon,</hi> another <hi>Engliſh Commentator,</hi> with great plainneſs gives it thus, <hi>At their juſtification he findeth them ungodly, and maketh them godly, and he doth it both by taking away the guilt and filth of their ſin.</hi> The Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is reckoned the Righteouſneſs of that Perſon who doth by Faith embrace him. <hi>Pitcairn</hi> ſays, Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here is taken in the ſame ſenſe as when God raiſeth the dead, and calls that which is not, to be, it being the term of alienation from which they are remov'd, from whence he bids farewell to all antecedent Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which ſome call inferiour, others in ſome manner or meaſure, others adminiſtrating, others <hi>ſine quo non,</hi> others Cauſes of poſſeſſion tho' not of right, for all Holineſs comes in as a way to the Kingdom, not as Cauſes of Rule. <hi>Dieſt</hi> thus, Juſtifying Grace finds him ſo in himſelf, but leaves him not ſo; <hi>For whom he juſtifies, them he ſanctifies.</hi> God Juſtifies us not as Holy in our ſelves, but as wanting righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he imputes a righteouſneſs to us. The Anger of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:200303:9"/>15. for want of Children, wanted a Pardon, even then before this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration about him, <hi>that his Faith was imputed to him for righteouſneſs. Theodore Szuingerus,</hi> whom <hi>Hottinger</hi> commends, and notwithout reaſon, as the beſt Commentator on this Epiſtle, compares the Text with 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.2. condemning the wicked to bring his way on his Head, and juſtifying the righteous to give him according to his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſolves the difficulty theſe two ways, 1. That the one is a Juſtification of a man's Cauſe, and the other a Juſtification of his Perſon, which is that in the Text. 2. This Juſtification of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly is not againſt a Law, but according to a Law; not without a righteouſneſs, but without his own only: Beſides, ſays he, Tho' it finds him ungodly, it leaves him not in his ungodlineſs. <hi>Bucer</hi> thus, If God ſhould not juſtifie the Wicked, none ſhould be juſtified, for the Lord find us all wicked before we are juſtified. <hi>Greneus,</hi> Tho' Man may not juſtifie the ungodly, God may, who has Power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give above Law. <hi>Pareus,</hi> Tho' they are juſtified who are wicked in themſelves, yet not without Cauſe, and againſt Rule, ſince there is a ſatisfaction in Chriſt. <hi>Marlorat</hi>'s <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Expoſition</hi> is thus, The firſt Bleſſing of Salvation is Pardon, and our Pardon being a Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it muſt be a juſtification of the Ungodly: What can they ſay to this, that are Slaves to their Belly, and yet brag of their Works? are they better than <hi>Abraham,</hi> who left his Countrey, redeem'd his Brother, and offered his Son, and Hop'd in his God againſt all Hope? but God in juſtifying leaves us not ungodly: Such therefore ought rather to fear they are not juſtify'd, becauſe they want the fruits of Juſtification, than brag they have the Cauſes of it in themſelves. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> thus, It's obſervable, the Diſcourſe is not about the way of living, but about the Cauſes of Salvation: He argues from contraries, and as <hi>Bucer</hi> ſays, not from words but ſentences. This Sentence is full of Energy, <hi>Believeth on him that juſtifies the ungodly;</hi> wherein both the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Faith and Righteouſneſs are contain'd. In ſhort, no body can come to the Righteouſneſs of Faith, but who is in himſelf Ungodly, for Faith adorns us with anothers Righteouſneſs, which it beggs of God; hence God is ſaid to juſtifie, when he freely forgives, and vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes to love them with whom he may be juſtly angry, <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Works they meerly cavil, who think all Works are not excluded, for he ſays not Works of the Law, but ſimply and without reſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Works of all kinds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beda venerabilis, Anno</hi> 700. ſays on this Text, What can he be but ungodly, until he be juſtified by Grace? for what Grace gives, it gives freely.—I dare not determine which of the two is the greater work,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:200303:9"/>to make a juſt man, or to juſtifie an ungodly man, both require equal power, but the latter greater grace or mercy: Boaſt not of thy works be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faith, for faith found thee a ſinner: — Man works not righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs until he be juſtified, and that begins with Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Aquinas,</hi> 1260. on this Text, To believe is the firſt act of Righteouſneſs which God works in us; by this man doth not merit righteouſneſs, but ſubject himſelf to God's juſtification, and ſo thereby receives its effect: This <hi>(ſays he)</hi> the Apoſtle proves, (1.) From <hi>David</hi>'s ſenſe, <hi>v.</hi> 6. He is a bleſſed man to whom God gives a righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without forgoing works. (2.) From <hi>David</hi>'s words, proving he had no righteouſneſs, for he needed for Orignal, Actual and Venial ſin, for the guilt of the Offence, Fact and Penalty of ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ambranat,</hi> a late Papiſt, 1665. <hi>Paris.</hi> The Apoſtle before acted an Orator by interrogations and frequent Queſtions, but now a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, with clouds of Arguments; before he oppos'd Gift and Works, now he oppoſes a Believer and Worker, a believer in him that endues the ungodly with his own righteouſneſs; <hi>Patiatur ergo ſi non operatur,</hi> when he is not a doer, he is made a receiver, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſays, <q rend="inline">Ungodly here comprehends all kind of Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, there is no kind that is excepted.</q> But there is no end of humane teſtimonies, for within my Cognizance I can reckon an hundred Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of this Epiſtle. I ſhall add two more of greateſt Authority in <hi>England:</hi> 1. The <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Aſſembly, I ſhall not quote the <hi>Annotations</hi> bearing their Name, but as I am inform'd on far leſs ground than <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Burgeſs</hi> his book of Juſtification, which was examin'd and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by them; one of his Titles is, That gracious works are not ſo much as the condition or cauſe, <hi>ſine qua non,</hi> of juſtification, and on this Text, <hi>p.</hi> 288. <hi>God doth account him as righteous, though a ſinner in himſelf:</hi> p. 290. <hi>While looking into our ſelves, we ſee nothing but matter of death and condemnation;</hi> and he has another Sermon, to prove that the Act of Faith is not imputed to juſtification, which the <hi>Aſſemblies Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm</hi> expreſly mentions. A Second Authority is the <hi>Articles</hi> and <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> But Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> has done that in a Sermon <hi>ex prepoſito.</hi> I ſhall conclude with theſe two noted Fathers, <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the former defines a worker to be not a tranſgreſſor of the Law, and a Non-worker a Tranſgreſſor; the latter in his Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions on this Epiſtle, <hi>Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 1193. <hi>Qui juſtificat impium de impio pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um facit juſtificatus eſt, ut juſtus ſit:</hi> Where I cannot omit, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers uſe the word juſtifie, for making juſt, though the uſual Scripture ſenſe is to acquit, abſolve; and the reaſon is evident, from the ſtrict union between them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.7. <hi>He that is freed from ſin,</hi> ſays our tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:200303:10"/>
               <hi>juſtified,</hi> ſays the Original; <hi>abſolv'd,</hi> or <hi>purged,</hi> ſays <hi>Baſil. M. deliver'd,</hi> ſays <hi>Theophilact.</hi> which ſtill confirms to me that the ſame grace which ſanctifies, juſtifies, though in different manners; the one by effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, the other relatively; the one by poſitive influence, the other by inſtitution; and <hi>Aug.</hi> p. 1195. ſhows this to be his ſenſe, <hi>opus enim gratiae eſt,</hi> its the work of grace, <hi>i. e. Gratiae donantis et dimittentis,</hi> pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace; <hi>ut moriamur peccato,</hi> that we dye to ſin; and indeed the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſuppoſes it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.2. <hi>How can we that are dead to ſin, live any longer therein?</hi> He had been ſpeaking of Juſtification, not Mortification; the Apoſtle ſuppoſes it to be one grace that did both, and that theſe two effects are twins of the ſame birth, though not both born one way, which may be for an argument to prove that juſtifying grace finds us Ungodly and Non-workers, ſince ſanctifying grace doth: And <hi>Auguſt. Tom.</hi> 6. in his Book <hi>de remiſſione &amp; meritis,</hi> 'twas of Juſtification, as that which comprehends in it Sanctification and Pardon both, for his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is thus, <hi>p.</hi> 659. <hi>&amp;c. What way we are juſtified in Chriſt, that way we are ſinful in the firſt Adam; but we are juſtified in Chriſt thorough pardon and ſanctification,</hi> Ergo, <hi>In</hi> Adam <hi>by guilt and pollution;</hi> and his Words thus we read, <q rend="inline">They are juſtified in Chriſt who believe in him, by reaſon of a ſecret communication and inſpiration of ſpiritual grace, by which every one cleaves to the Lord, and is one ſpirit with him, — <hi>Adam</hi> thorough his own ſin begot guilty perſons, and Chriſt by his grace begets pardon'd perſons.</q> This was wrote againſt <hi>Pelagius,</hi> who ſaid, We ſinn'd only in <hi>Adam</hi> by imitation: And the ſucceſs is obſerv'd by <hi>Janſenus</hi> in his <hi>Auguſtinus,</hi> p. 103. that he brought <hi>Pelagius</hi> to own pardoning grace to be free without conditions, but not ſanctifying grace: <q rend="inline">Great is the bleſſedneſs, ſays <hi>Pelagius,</hi> to obtain grace, <hi>i. e.</hi> (the grace of remiſſion) without the works of the Law, and exerciſe of Repentance; for <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. <hi>The gifts of God are without repentance;</hi> He that believes in Chriſt in that day, becomes as he who has fulfill'd the whole Law:</q> And the ſame Author, <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 33. Who knew well <hi>Auguſtines</hi> mind, and ſaid, without that owning of grace which <hi>Auſtins</hi> doctrine contains, Chriſtian Humility is not attainable, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving read him all ten times, and ſuch Books thirty times, ſays, that the grace of remiſſion of ſin belongs to the gift of habitual grace, not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter actual helping grace; which, ſays he, my Author delights to call medicinal grace to nature, in its ſick, yea, dead ſtate. Fewer words are about this grace, becauſe <hi>Pelagius</hi> owns nature guilty, but not hurt or wounded by ſin, and ſo needed pardon, but not grace to regenerate. But 2ly. A greater than <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is here, the Spirit of God conſtantly unites them two, and who dare ſeparate them, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 32.2. <hi>Whoſe ſin
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:200303:10"/>is covered, and in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile:</hi> The Scriptures the Apoſtle quotes on the Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the fleſh,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.14. Pardoning grace was abundant toward a perſecuting <hi>Saul,</hi> together with Faith and Love, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. <hi>All things belonging to life eternal and godlineſs,</hi> — He calls to Glory and Virtue at once, by that call are given precious promiſes, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>By the waſhing of Regeneration, and renewing of the Holy Ghoſt, — being juſtified by his grace,</hi> Gal. 5.24. <hi>They that are in Chriſt have crucified the fleſh, with its affections and luſts,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.27. <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, he is a New Creature,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.11. <hi>But ye are ſanctified, but ye are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified,</hi> &amp;c. I cannot but take Notice of what gave birth and occaſion to the Popiſh Errors, who make juſtification and ſanctification one and the ſame; or, that the one is the other, <hi>viz.</hi> The Fathers expreſſions, who underſtood them ſtill of diſtinct natures, but given at once. A ring may enrich a Woman by its native value, and marry her by legal conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; a King may arm a Man with a Sword, and ſignifie his royal favour by its gift. The Grace that doth <hi>juſtum facere,</hi> doth <hi>gratum facere,</hi> makes him juſt in himſelf, and ſignifies his guilt pardon'd, and his perſon accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in favour.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. As Humane Teſtimony and Divine, ſo reaſon unites them, can a man have faith, that is, juſtifying and ſaving, and not be regenerate? faith and love being the two firſt branches of the root of Grace, the Heart and Head of the New-Creature, and can a man be regenerate, and not juſtified? can he have the greater priviledge, and not the leſſer? can he be a Son, and not a free Subject?</p>
            <p>I might bring a 3d. Argument from the nature of the Subject, <hi>viz.</hi> That before Converſion and Regeneration man can do no ſpiritual good thing, there is no action of ours acceptable to God but thorough Chriſt, which ſuppoſes an intereſt in him, and union with him; <hi>without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God;</hi> the ſacrifice, the plowing, the praying of the wicked is ſin; and the foundation of it is, <hi>We are dead in ſins and treſpaſſes,</hi> until the minute that God quickens us, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1. and what can come from ſtinking Carcaſſes in the graves, but ſavour of death, a loathſom ſmell. We cannot have faith, until God gives it, its the Gift of God, a faith of the operation of God, and he gives it thorough Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Chriſt is the author and finiſher of our faith:</hi> I know no Commentator that denies his merit to come in for its proper influence to the gift of Faith. Can an evil tree bring forth ſuch fruits, or a branch not ingrafted in the true vine? when we have no ſpiritual diſcerning, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. and having our hearts alienated from the Life of God, thorough the ignorance that is in us, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.17. What good can we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:200303:11"/>do? Now no giſt leſs then quickning, regenerating grace, can do this. The anſwer given to this uſually by <hi>Arminians,</hi> and men tending that way, is, that Regeneration, Creation, Reſurrection, are but Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical Terms; and one thing they fail in likeneſs is, that the one is wrought by degrees, the other inſtantaneous; the one is on paſſive mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that yields according to the power put forth on them, but this is on the will of Man that can reſiſt a ſufficient grace, to bring forth ſuch effects. <hi>Reſp.</hi> This the Scripture favours not, for it ſays, <hi>God works to will as well as to be able;</hi> and it ſays, <hi>When we were dead he quicken'd us.</hi> 2. This was the <hi>Pelagian</hi> Error, that God gave grace to be able, but not to be willing
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jan. Aug. To.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note>. 3. It would be Grace reſtoring to <hi>Adams</hi> condition, to be able to do good or evil: 4. This diſtinction of ſufficient and efficacious grace, <hi>Janſenus</hi> ſays, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> nor none of the <hi>Latin Fathers</hi> knew, nor any general Council ever did determine
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>To.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c</hi> 29.</note>. About 5 for grace to have its efficacy from the corrupt will of Man, is enmity, to be the Author of Love from ſufficient grace, it is not; that brings not forth the effect, there is nothing elſe in the will of Man: If it be another addition of grace, the former was not ſufficient; and indeed where its not able to conquer the will of man, and bring forth its effect, to make man willing, it is not. But this were to leave the Queſtion about juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying grace, and to diſpute about ſanctifying grace.</p>
            <p>A 4th. Argument, is from the nature and the kind of juſtifying acts: As to its Original, it's gracious, as to its Obiect, it's pardon, put theſe two together, a gracious pardon, and it ſuppoſes the Object under great guilt and miſery: For, (1.) Grace is goodneſs in all its variety and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; when the Lord proclaims his own graciouſneſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. He deſcribes it by abundance of Goodneſs and Truth, tenderneſs of mercy, and longneſs of ſuffering, and this as the ſpring of pardoning grace; <hi>Keeping mercy for thouſands, forgiving iniquity, and tranſgreſſion, and ſin.</hi> Where the perſon is juſt by a conſtituted Law, there is no need of ſuch amplifications of Goodneſs; for if it be an eaſie Law, the grace was in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king law, and not in juſtifying by the Law. (2.) Grace is goodneſs flowing from the Heart of the Giver; its called <hi>gratia gratum faciens,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it renders the perſon acceptable and lovely in the ſight of God; hence it bears the name of Love, thorough the Book of <hi>Canticles,</hi> Chap. 8.6. <hi>Set me as a ſeal on thy heart, as a ſeal upon thine arm:</hi> So is every object of Free-grace, his Love is fixed on them, and hence the arm of his Power protects them: But this Love of Grace is incomparable, its ſtronger than Death, for at once it delivers from a legal and ſpiritual Death, the guilt and the power of ſin, and him that hath the power of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:200303:11"/>Death, that is the Devil; as <hi>cruel as the Grave,</hi> that devours all before it; <hi>The Coals thereof are coals of fire, no waters can quench it, nor floods drown it:</hi> And as its full, ſo its free; <hi>If a man would give all the ſubſtance of his houſe for love, it would be utterly contemn'd.</hi> A (3.) Ingredient of grace, is mercy, pardoning grace and mercy are but different names of the ſame thing, and ſuppoſe the Object in a miſerable condition, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.32. <hi>God hath concluded them all in unbelief, that he might have mercy on all:</hi> And this mercy is preventing mercy, for the Apoſtle ſpeaking to the very ſame purpoſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.20. ſays, <hi>I was found of them that ſought me not, I was made manifeſt in them that askt not for me:</hi> And yet farther, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. He ſhews, that all the cauſes, conditions and motives of Mercy, are to be ſought for in the diſpoſition of the Author, and not the diſpoſition of the ſubject: <hi>That the purpoſe of God according to election might ſtand, not of Works, but of him that calleth.</hi> But the Name grace ſeems to import ſomewhat higher than all this, it ſpeaks excluſiveneſs of conditions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Being juſtified freely by his grace;</hi> that is, ſaith the <hi>Neat Witſius,</hi> without any cauſe or condition. (2.) It ſpeaks ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>John</hi> 1.16. <hi>Of his fulneſs we have received grace for grace:</hi> Coloſ. 2.10. <hi>In him dwelleth all the fulneſs of the Godhead bodily, and ye are compleat in him:</hi> And it ſpeaks perſeverance, for the Covenant of Grace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the ſure mercies of <hi>David,</hi> Pſalm 89.33. <hi>Though I viſit their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with ſtripes, nevertheleſs my loving-kindneſs will I not utterly take from them.</hi> It ſpeaks the Object in a moſt wretched condition, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1, 7. <hi>I won't contend for ever, neither will I be always wroth;</hi> though my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger hath an end, my mercy hasn't; <hi>for the ſpirit would fail before me, and the ſouls which I have made;</hi> as they cannot convert themſelves, ſo they can't bear my endleſs wrath: <hi>For the iniquity of his Covetuouſneſs was I wroth, and ſmote him, I hid me, and was worth, and he went on fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in the way of his heart:</hi> A moſt deſperate Condition; the eaſieſt law in the world could ſpeak no comfort to him, but grace can: <hi>I have ſeen his ways, and will heal him; I will lead him, and reſtore comforts to him:</hi> Tho' there be no matter in the ſubject to bring Comfort out of, my grace hath a creative power; <hi>I create the fruit of the lips, peace to him that is far off,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(Laſtly,)</hi> Soveraignity is an ingredient in grace: We read of grace upon the Throne, a Throne of Grace, all pure grace: Where the Tranſactions and Dipenſations are according to Law, there is no place for over-ruling Soveraignity, but this juſtification is a diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from a Throne of Grace, and the very end of it is to glorifie that grace, <hi>verſes</hi> 16, 17. <hi>It is of faith, that it might be by grace:</hi> All Laws, and tranſgreſſions of Laws, all Diſpenſations of Providence, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, all Manifeſtations of other Attributes, are for the diſcovery of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:200303:12"/>the height of this Throne: <hi>All is for the praiſe of the glory of his Grace:</hi> And the whole of this grace receives a luſtre in its firſt preventive act towards a ſinner; for as he is God of all Grace, he calls us into his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal glory. If all the other ſtreams of grace finds us in our ſin and guilt, elective grace, redeeming grace, calling and converting grace, why ſhould it be ſuppoſed or conjectured, that pardoning grace doth not find us ſo to? when the very formality of the object is ſinfulneſs: The Text tells us, tis a covering of ſin, a not imputing of ſin, a forgiving of Iniquity, a blotting out our tranſgreſſions, a removing of them from us as far as the <hi>Eaſt</hi> is from the <hi>Weſt;</hi> an act that renders God a Peerleſs God, and therefore ſuppoſes our condition worſt; <hi>Who is a God like unto thee?</hi> Micah 7.18. <hi>that pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſgreſſion of the remnant rf his Heritage, he retaineth not his anger for ever, becauſe he delighteth in mercy; he will turn again, he will have compaſſion upon us, he will ſubdue our iniquities, and caſt all their ſins in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the depth of the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The only Uſe that I ſhall make of this is to linners, who are in their Ungodlineſs, and without Works, and whoſe Conſciences tells them ſo; the doctrine ſpeaks this to you, that you have as great reaſon, and as great encouragement to come to this throne of Grace, and to ſue out for a pardon in the Name of Chriſt, as any others. There was an univerſal command to the Apoſtles, to preach the Goſpel to every creature, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. And that commiſſion ſtands a Directory to every one, that is a Servant of Chriſt in the Office of the Goſpel; and as Chriſt invites, ſo the Church of Chriſt invites alſo; the Language of a ſanctified Soul over a Brother or Siſter, according to the fleſh, is like that of the Spouſe, <hi>We have a little Siſter, and ſhe hath no breaſts, what ſhall we do for our Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the day ſhe ſhall be ſpoken for? The Bride ſaith come, and the Spirit ſaith come,</hi> Rev. 22.17. And their joint voice is, <hi>Whoſoever will, let him come.</hi> Beware of being guilty of quenching or provoking the Spirit; may be your Conſciences bear witneſs, that there is a higher Meſſenger ſent to offer you a pardon this day than the voice of any clay Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet; but, whether you find any ſuch quickner and enabler, rendring you willing and deſirous to ſay, <hi>Whether ſhall we go? for thou haſt the words of eternal life; in thee have we righteouſneſs and ſtrength, by thee only will we make mention of thy Name: Thy face Lord we will ſeek; Caſt the skirts of thy Garments over us:</hi> I ſay, whether you feel this influence or not, it is this external offer, that both gives you right to come to a pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, for forgiveneſs of ſins, thorough the righteouſneſs of Chriſt only, and makes it your duty, however torn the Garments of your own Righteouſneſs are; or your conſciences thereby, to depend upon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:200303:12"/>our Lord Jeſus Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs, by which the Law gains its end, and the Government full ſatisfaction, and in this truſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance to come to the Throne of Grace, and ſue in his name for the forgiveneſs of your ſin, and juſtification of your perſons: I ſay, the offer gives you a right. In other tranſactions with men, there are theſe three ways of conveyance of a right, (1.) The Offer of his Eſtate, or Goods, or Priviledge. (2.) The price that I pay him for it. (3.) The Writings that contain its Extent and Title. (4.) The Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſeizing, or taking poſſeſſion; all theſe go to compleat the right, but if we had to do with an Unchangeable Perſon, full of goodneſs and kind deſigns towards us, he would never go back from his firſt Offer, that would bring him on to compleat the Title in all the reſt. Now here you have the offer of a Pardon, and the offer of a Sonſhip, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance with it; the God that cannot lye nor change has made it: Here you have the tenour and extent of the bleſſing in the Covenant of Grace, the Spirit of God has penn'd it, and you may ſee the bleſſing is great, and the tenour ſo ordered, that it may reach you ſinners: He tells you, the price is paid already, it is 1600 years ſince 'twas laid down; the invitation is, <hi>All things are ready, come unto the feaſt:</hi> The Queſtion is only, Whether the World or this is worth your Choice? Is not a Pardon deſirable? Have we no longings to come out of this priſon, where there's no water? will we adventure the paying the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing our ſelves, rather than to be obliged to Chriſt for a full payment? but this offer comprehends a Command in its boſome; if our Unworthineſs renders us aſham'd, and our Guiltineſs afraid, and makes us apt to ſay, <hi>Depart from me, for I am a ſinful man;</hi> Let conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of duty oblige us to draw nigh, for <hi>this is his Commandment, that we ſhould believe on the name of his Son Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> And none of us can ſay, but this command reaches us, elſe unbelief would not be the condemnation of the World. Chriſt was griev'd for the hardneſs of their hearts that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd not, and wept over an obſtinate <hi>jeruſalem,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Oh if thou hadſt known at leaſt in this thy day the things which belong unto thy peace!</hi> Now which of theſe two doth your Hearts conclude will be the iſſue of this offer, either <hi>They would not come to me that they might have life;</hi> or, <hi>Thine they are, and thou gaveſt them me, and they have kept thy Word: I have given to them the words which thou gaveſt me, and they have received them; Holy Father, keep thro' thine own Name thoſe whom thou haſt given me.</hi> The grand Offence that we ſtumble at commonly, if our Conſciences anſwer one another, is the particular circumſtances and aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our particular ſins: And yet 'tis a very unreaſonable Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it ſavours rather of the darkneſs of Hell than the light of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:200303:13"/>above, or Faith below. Should we delay the looking after a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, becauſe we are very guilty? ſhould ſinners not accept of the Son of God, Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe God ſent him to bleſs us, in turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us from our Iniquities? did we ever read of any that Chriſt threw off as incurable, becauſe his Satisfaction or the Tenour of the Goſpel could not reach them? is our Condition worſe than <hi>Manaſſe</hi>'s or <hi>Saul</hi>'s? has our delay been longer than the Thief on the Croſs, or our filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs viler than <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi>'s? There are theſe four Conditions that Chriſt has ſpecified in his Goſpel to prevent Exceptions. (1.) Prophane Perſons, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.32. <hi>The Publicans and the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots believ'd in him.</hi> (2.) Secure Perſons, like lukewarm <hi>Laodicea,</hi> that was inſenſible of her own miſery, yet he ſtands knocking at their door, and offering, that if any of them, the worſt of them, would open, he would come into them, and ſup with them: His fullneſs ſhould have a feaſt of Glory and Honour, and their emptineſs ſhould ſup on his fullneſs. (3.) The Hypocrites: Of all Conditions that ſeems to be the moſt dangerous; ſuch were the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. <hi>Hypocrites;</hi> yet how often would Chriſt have gathered theſe under the Wings of his Righteouſneſs, <hi>Ver.</hi> 37. Yet theſe Invitations were not altogether fruitleſs. <hi>Saul</hi> was a Phariſee, <hi>Nichodemus</hi> was a Phariſee: The Balm of <hi>Gilead</hi> is a Medicine can cure this deſperate diſtemper, and the Blood of Chriſt can cover the guilt of it. Another gauling circumſtance to a tender, or a wounded conſcience, is backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, falling away from firſt Love, and walking unſuitably to preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, preventive mercies; but in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 1. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. How many invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to a backſliding-Church, backſlidden from the greateſt Priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ever Church received in the World, backſlidden into the vileſt abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that ever people were guilty of, Idolatry, worſhipping a Stock or Stone for their God, and yet with what earneſt intreaties, and what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive arguments does he plead with them: <hi>How ſhall I give thee up E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim, I remember thee ſtill! the love of thy eſpouſal was pleaſant to me: O Iſrael! I am married to thee, why ſhould there be a divorce? Come, and let us reaſon together, though thy Iniquities were as crimſon, and thy tranſgreſſions as ſcarlet, I will heal thy backſlidings, I will love thee freely, and receive thee gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly.</hi> To expect to come any other way, or upon our delay to come on better terms, were to pervert the very Nature of the Goſpel, and ſay, we would not be ſaved in God's method, but our own; <hi>Not by works of righteouſneſs which we have done, but according to his mercy hath he ſaved us.</hi> Will we reject the way and method that all the cloud of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes were ſav'd in, and will we be ſaved in that way never one was ſav'd in? they attain not unto the Law of righteouſneſs, becauſe they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:200303:13"/>ſought it, or as it were by the works of the Law. Chriſt is the true and living way; is there any fault we can find in him? is he not able to ſave to the uttermoſt? is there any righteouſneſs like his? it's ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting: Can we give any ſatisfaction to divine Government like what he hath given? Can we bear the Curſe and drink the Cup that he did? is he not altogether lovely in himſelf, and altogether fit for us? infinite Wiſdom and infinite Goodneſs, fitted and prepared him and is he not willing that we ſhould ſhare of his righteouſneſs? doth not his offer ſpeak it? <hi>Come unto me all ye that are heavy laden;</hi> doth not his tears and his ſorrows over them that refuſe and defer ſpeak it? doth not that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Chearfulneſs he undertook his Work with ſpeak it? <hi>Lo, I come, in the volume of thy Book 'tis written of me;</hi> thy Law is within my Heart, the bent of my Heart is to do thy will; and that deſire left him not, nor ever was abated under the heat of the day, and heavieſt of the curſe: <hi>I have a baptiſm to be baptized with, and how am I ſtraightned till it be accompliſht? with deſire have I deſired to eat this paſſover; having lov'd his own, he lov'd them to the end:</hi> And will not all this Love towards us kindle ſome ſparks of deſire in our frozen breaſts? don't we think they deſerve an <hi>Anathema Maranatha,</hi> that love not this Lord Jeſus Chriſt? The depth and height, the breadth and length of his Love paſſeth all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, he was full of Love, as he was a man; he lov'd <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſo, and he lov'd the young man in the Goſpel ſo; he was full of love, as he was a Mediator: Such was that love, whoſe dimenſions our narrow minds can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpan, but he was more full of love as he was God: God is love, and God ſo lov'd the World to give his Son; is not this <hi>Emanuel</hi> worthy of our acceptation? Gods infinite Wiſdom found him, can we find a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or do without him? have we no ſelf-love for our ſouls? what will become of us without a pardon? can we bear the curſe of the Law, or wrath of God? is it not worthy acceptance on any terms? but what terms can be better, it's come to God and beg Repentance; the Almighty makes the heart ſoft; <hi>I will pour down the ſpirit of Grace and ſupplication, and they ſhall look on him whom they have pierced, and mourn: Obj.</hi> But com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God is believing, and I cannot believe until he gives me faith, which is not yet? <hi>Reſp.</hi> Put that to Tryal, what if the Spirit of God be now directing and quickning thy conſcience to this Work? and the Language of thy heart is, ſtay until time for Prayer at night, or to morrow; you will think of it; Alas, Alas, this is the common anſwer to Gods Spirit himſelf, what wonder the Prophets cry, <hi>To whom is the Arm of the Lord revealed?</hi> Lord bleſs this for better fruits.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:200303:14"/>
            <head>SERMON II.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. IV. 5, 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>— His Faith is counted for Righteouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>Even as David alſo deſcribeth the bleſſedneſs of the Man unto whom God imputeth righteouſneſs without works.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the Former Diſcourſe you have an account of the condition and diſpoſition of the ſubject of Juſtification, in this I propoſe an account of the Goſpel-method, how God juſtifies the ungodly; it is a different Queſtion from that of the convicted <hi>Jews,</hi> Acts 2. <hi>Men and Brethren what ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi> This is, What doth God do to ſave a ſinner that has contemn'd his Authority, brought diſorder into his Government, violated his holy, juſt and good Laws, and goes on frowardly without repenting of what he has done? the Rebel doth not, will not yield, ſhall the Governour yield? doth God need us? how is it poſſible to reconcile God's juſtice and Man's enmity? how can a juſt God juſtifie an ungodly perſon? The Apoſtle makes but two ſentences of the Anſwer: 1. He imputes his Faith to Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. 2. He ſays, that Righteouſneſs is imputed to Bleſſedneſs. The nature of the Diſcourſe is didactick, inſtructive, and there are theſe three <hi>Queſtions</hi> that are matters of no ſmall Moment nor mean Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies: 1. Whoſe this Righteouſneſs is: 2. What is the importance of the imputation of righteouſneſs to a man for bleſſedneſs: 3. What is the meaning of Faiths being imputed to righteouſneſs. I ſhall only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe what I am moſt perſwaded of to be the true ſenſe of them, and what perſwades me to be of that mind, without uſing means to confute others: I ſhall leave them to the ſame liberty I preſume on. As to the firſt there are but two general Opinions, <hi>viz.</hi> Either Chriſts or our own, though each are ſubdivided, in what righteouſneſs of Chriſts it is, or of ours. My Buſineſs is to confirm and eſtabliſh this truth, that this Righteouſneſs in the Text imputed for bleſſedneſs, is the righteouſneſs inherent in our bleſſed Mediator, and if this one Character of being without works were to be underſtood abſtracted from the Apoſtles deſign, which is not to exclude works from righteouſneſs, but our works and our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I ſhould think it a diſtinguiſhing Mark between Chriſt's righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:200303:14"/>and any mans elſe; for the righteouſneſs of Works conſiſts in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the preceptive part of the Law, but Chriſts Righteouſneſs conſiſts alſo in a conformity to the ſanction of the Law: He was made a curſe for us, and that is not to work in the Scripture phraſe, but to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, though in it ſelf hard work, even Soul-travel; but doubting the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of this, I ſhall propoſe others of greater ſtability. (1.) That Righteouſneſs that is the cauſe of Bleſſedneſs, and whoſe fruit is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin, is the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, for there is no other name given under Heaven, and therefore no other righteouſneſs by which a Man can be ſaved; but the righteouſneſs in the Text is the cauſe of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs and pardon, there muſt be ſome near connexion between par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and imputation of righteouſneſs, elſe the Apoſtle did miſtake the Prophets ſence, ſaying, he meant imputation of righteouſneſs unto bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs, when he ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven;</hi> the connexion is either pretended to be that of the cauſe to the effect, or ſome kind of requiſite condition. They who ſay, this is our own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, are for the latter, who ſay, its Chriſt's, are for the former, and with reaſon; for our own righteouſneſs wants not works, our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faith is not without works, but this is. 2ly. The righteouſneſs of Chriſt and our pardon are more neceſſarily united than our faith, for pardon is as ſoon given as it: Theſe are more likely ſences, when <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſe ſin is forgiven,</hi> to mean, bleſſed is he who has an intereſt in Chriſt, and his ſatisfaction, than to mean bleſſed is he who repents: Nay, the Prophet adds that as another thing, <hi>Bleſſed is he in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile, i. e.</hi> Bleſſed is the pardon'd man, and the ſincere man. 3ly. He is ungodly when forgiven, therefore his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is not the condition of it. 4ly. <hi>C.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 25. To declare his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs for the remiſſion of ſins that are paſt, why ſhould we think the Terms connexed, other than what before he unites as cauſe and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect? this is to unite what the Apoſtle ſeparates, our Works and Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and ſeparate what he unites, Chriſt righteouſneſs and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. (2.) It is not ſuppoſable to think, that Chriſt's righteouſneſs or ſatisfaction ſhould be no where mention'd in this diſpute about the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Juſtification, when its confeſt that that is the grand and only me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting cauſe: It is ſtrange, that he ſhould diſpute about the cauſe of pardon, and yet never mention the true cauſe; but inſtead of it, always a little petty requiſite without any cauſality at all, and the more ſtrange, that he ſhould ſo frequently mention that cauſe under the name of Chriſt's blood, and his being deliver'd for our offences, the matter of his righteouſneſs in the context, and ſeldom ever the effect without it; but when he calls it by the name of righteouſneſs, the proper name by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:200303:15"/>which it ſaves us, for his blood ſaves us as it is a righteouſneſs, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the law of Redemption, that wherein the Law obtain'd its end, then it ſhould not be eſteem'd his, but our own: (3.) We may learn whoſe righteouſneſs it is that is mention'd in the diſpute, by what was propos'd in the Theſe or Doctrine to be diſputed, which he propoſes both negatively and affirmatively, <hi>viz.</hi> Juſtified not by our righteouſneſs or works, but God's; we are juſtified by Gods righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, this he propoſes <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. as the grand end of the Goſpel; <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the righteouſneſs of God revealed from faith;</hi> ſurely God's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Faith by which its receiv'd, are diſtinct things, from thence to <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>c.</hi> 3. he proves, that all our own righteouſneſs is entirely rejected from any intereſt in this affair, and again <hi>v.</hi> 21. propoſes thus, the righteouſneſs of God to be that, which he now undertakes to prove to be the only righteouſneſs we are juſtified by: <hi>But now the righteouſneſs of God without the law is manifeſted;</hi> and that by God he means Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3, 4. may be eaſily learn'd from his words, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the righteouſneſs of God, for Chriſt is the end of the Law for righteouſneſs;</hi> and that it is not call'd the righteouſneſs of God becauſe his gift, we may learn from <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Your faith is ſpoken of thoroughout the world:</hi> Faith is a work, this is the work of God to believe on his name, and faith is a righteouſneſs, for there is a conformity to the Law in it, but it is ours, <hi>your faith;</hi> faith differs from this righteouſneſs as the act and object, <hi>Righteouſneſs of God reveal'd from faith to faith:</hi> What unprejudic'd man would call that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and faith the ſame? faith differs from it as the effect from the cauſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Have obtain'd the like precious faith with us, thorough the righteouſneſs of God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Who would wiſh for a plainer expreſſion to prove that the gift of Faith is the fruit of Chriſt's merit? and therefore this righteouſneſs muſt be imputed to us, before that gift be poſſeſs'd by us. (4.) The Epithets of this righteouſneſs ſpeaks it to be Chriſts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21, 22, 24. 1. Its the righteouſneſs of God; God was Author, Owner, Contriver, Acter, Giver, Subject of this righteouſneſs, it deſerves the name by way of Eminence; who could contrive it but his Wiſdom, give it but his Grace, bear it but his Patience, work it but his Power, poſſeſs it but his Fulneſs? 2. <hi>Without the Law,</hi> on two accounts, both as to the perſon, and as to the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. (1.) The perſon, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. <hi>Was made under the law;</hi> he came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it by his own voluntary choice, not natural neceſſity, as we are, hence without the Law. (2.) The Righteouſneſs was, that no precept of the Law requir'd to dye or ſuffer, that was none of its duties or righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; it was its penalty in caſe of Unrighteouſneſs. (3.) Its a righteouſneſs <hi>now manifeſted;</hi> faith and repentance has ſhin'd in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:200303:15"/>of the Patriarchs and Prophets ever ſince <hi>Adam,</hi> Heb. 11. <hi>Abel, Noah, Enoch</hi> believ'd; indeed Chriſt's was a new kind the World never ſaw before. (4.) <hi>It was witneſs'd by the Law and the Prophets;</hi> if we take the Law for the books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they bear witneſs to it. <hi>Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, and it was imputed to him for righteouſneſs; the bruiſing his heel, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. witneſſes his ſuffering the principal matter of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: If we take it for the Typical Law, that witneſſed to it, for all the ſacrifices were Types, and Types are viſible Prophecies, and all the Language is, the Meſſias was to ſuffer in the room of others, to obey a Law for others; and the Prophets witneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. <hi>Surely ſhall one ſay, in the Lord have I righteouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 23.6. <hi>The Lord our righteouſneſs,</hi> Dan. 9. <hi>To bring in everlaſting righteouſneſs:</hi> There are the Teſtimonies of three Prophets, — <hi>To him gave all the Prophets witneſs.</hi> (5.) It was a righteouſneſs convey'd thorough faith, put on them that believe, <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>which is by faith of Jeſus Chriſt unto all, and upon all them that believe.</hi> (6.) A righteouſneſs that conſiſt in a conformity to a Law, which to us is a Law of Faith, not Works. We are bound to believe his Obedience to all the Law in the Covenant of Redemption, but not to work one bit of it: Hence we being juſtified by that righteouſneſs, our boaſting is excluded, <hi>v.</hi> 27. (7.) A faith that conſiſts in ſhedding of blood, in ſuffering, <hi>v.</hi> 25. Theſe two are to the ſame effect; <hi>Thorough faith in his blood, and righteouſneſs by faith.</hi> (8.) A righteouſneſs whoſe fruit is remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſin, <hi>v.</hi> 24. <hi>To declare his righteouſneſs for the remiſſion of ſins that are paſs'd;</hi> the ſame Coherence that is in the Text between imputation of righteouſneſs and pardon. (9) <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. A righteouſneſs wherein the Law attain'd its full end, the Subject Life and Happineſs, and the Law-giver honour and glory. (10.) A righteouſneſs, the gift whereof glorifies grace to the uttermoſt, the righteouſneſs of an Angel is not ſuch a gift as this is. (5.) Its a righteouſneſs that is made ours: As <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt offence or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs was made ours, that never inher'd in us, but death came on us by it, then it has ſome relation to us, and we to it; this is at large in <hi>C.</hi> 5. where the Author of this righteouſneſs is plainly call'd the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and if that be not plain enough, <hi>v.</hi> 21. he is call'd <hi>Jeſus Chriſt our Lord:</hi> And that its made ours, 1. By a gracious gift; <hi>abundance of grace, and of the gift of righteouſneſs:</hi> 2. It ſtill remain'd inherent in him alone, for <hi>juſtification of life came upon all men, by the righteouſneſs of one:</hi> If it were ours, there muſt be as many righteouſneſes as juſtifications; but here, <hi>by the obedience of one many are made righteous.</hi> 3. Its convey'd thorough a Law: The word <hi>made</hi> imports a legal conſtitution, and the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s caſe ſhews it; <hi>until the Law ſin was in the world; ſin is not imputed when there is no law;</hi> wherever imputation is there is a Law; the Hoſtage
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:200303:16"/>cannot ſuffer for his King or Country but by ſome Law; Chriſt was made ſin for us only by Law, and we the righteouſneſs of God in him by law. The Debtor is reliev'd thorough the Sureties diſcharge by a Law, and this Law is the Law of Faith, that we ought daily to ſtudy; the Law was, <hi>If thou as ſponſor wilt dye for them, they ſhall live; if thou wilt go under the curſe of their Law, take their Law-place, for thy ſake they ſhall have the place of Sons.</hi> Its much harder to me to comprehend how <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt offence ſhould be imputed to us for death, then Chriſts righteouſneſs for life; and it ſeems worthy obſervation, that the one imputation is never very clearly reveal'd, until the other be ſet over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. The Apoſtle thereby tells us we are no loſers, but gainers by it; an imputed righteouſneſs may well free from an imputed guilt, and commends that righteouſneſs imputed, for it frees from more than that, <hi>viz.</hi> from all guilt. This 5th. <hi>C.</hi> gives account of the Original of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, how it comes that one ſhould be juſtified by anothers righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or condem'd by anothers ſin. <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 7.24. among his many learned Enquiries in his latter days, enquires after the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of ſin, how a righteous man ſhould become a ſinner: <hi>One thing have I found, that God made man upright, but we have found out many inventions.</hi> The Apoſtles enquiry is of a greater depth, how one mans guilt or righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſhould be convey'd to another? <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin or Chriſt's righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. (6.) Its a righteouſneſs made ours, as he was ſin, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. which did never inhere in him. (7.) From the very Title of imputed, but that will be made clear in the 2d. general head, to which I now come, and whether I refer a conſiderable Queſtion belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this, <hi>viz. What righteouſneſs of Chriſt is it that is imputed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. As to the ſecond Queſtion, <hi>What is meant by Imputation of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs?</hi> I ſhall begin with the ſignification of the word, which as others is tranſlated from humane uſe to ſignifie by ſimilitude ſome divine thing. Putation, thinking belongs to the Art of Logic, and in the Greek the words are Conjugates, branches of the ſame root, and in Hebrew <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is uſed for thoughts too; <hi>The Lord knoweth the thoughts of men, that they are vanity,</hi> Pſal. 94.11. (2.) Computation belongs to Arithmetick, and Greek Authors explain this word by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate, number or reckon, and as the Art of Logick has the name from the Greek, the Art of Arithmetick, Accompting, in Hebrew, has its Name from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſee <hi>Munſter</hi>'s Lexicon; and ſo the Scripture uſes the word, <hi>Lev.</hi> 25.27. <hi>Let him count the years of the ſale thereof:</hi> Eccl. 7.26. <hi>Counting one by one, to find out the accompt.</hi> (3.) Imputation is an applying of Accompts, and the things valued and eſteemed thereby; it is accompt, aſſign or aſcribe, by way of counting and reckoning to ſome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:200303:16"/>particular perſons. We have here then the righteouſneſs of Chriſt as a rich treaſure of Grace in the bank of God; it's one individual Jewel given of God for the redemption of ſlaves, and its value is ſo great, and the way it's communicated being by Accompts, it may be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to pay for the redemption of Millions, all at various times and places. We have God repreſented as a great Merchant, with his rich Fund, and his Books of Accompts, the Merchandize <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. <hi>Is better than that of ſilver or gold:</hi> Rev. 3. the Naked may buy garments of Righteouſneſs; and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. they may buy without Money or Price. Among theſe Books <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. <hi>The books were open'd, and another book was open'd:</hi> There is one Book that is call'd <hi>The Lambs Book,</hi> Rev. 13.8. <hi>Whoſe Names are not written in the book of Life of the Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the World.</hi> There are two Books of Life, one for Angels by their own inherent righteouſneſs, another for fallen Man, who obtain it thorough the Death of the Lamb, his paſſive righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: In this book Chriſt has Credit for the redemption of all, agreed for between the Father and Son, and when a perſons Name is put in that Book, Chriſt's righteouſneſs is transferr'd to him for Life, for a ſalvation from all evil, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Thy People ſhall be deliver'd, every one that ſhall be found written in the Book:</hi> Luk. 10.20. <hi>Rejoice that your Names are written in Heaven:</hi> We may then ſee what the Imputation of Chriſt's righteouſneſs to us is, it was the putting our Names in among the Number for whom Chriſt dy'd, it's having all Chriſt did and ſuffer'd put ſo to our accompt, that we may actually partake of all the Bleſſings God's goodneſs and grace deſign'd for us, but the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs'd Law render'd it inconſiſtent with the Governour's Authority, Honour and Wiſdom to confer it upon us; the way this impediment and bar was remov'd, was by the ſufferings of <hi>Immanuel.</hi> Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is either the application of that benefit from Eternity in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Decree of God, or the actual inveſting the Perſon with it in time: It's my preſent Light, that the Imputation of Righteouſneſs to Bleſſedneſs was the eternal act, and the imputation of Faith to Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs the temporal; the former was 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. a purpoſe of conferring this grace and gift of Righteouſneſs upon us in Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World began. There was a double Gift ſet down in that Book by him that is God of all grace, ſovereign Proprietor. 1. We were given to Chriſt; <hi>Thine they were, and thou gaveſt them me.</hi> 2. Chriſt's Righteouſneſs was given to us by his Conſent, he became ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, his Name was put in our Book of Debt and Death, and ours in his of Righteouſneſs and Life.</p>
            <p>Two things need proof here: 1. That Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:200303:17"/>transferr'd in its Value and Virtue to us in way of accompt. 2. That that was from Eternity. The firſt is manifeſt from the Text, for one cannot be juſtified without an antecedent righteouſneſs; the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worker and Ungodly perſon has no righteouſneſs of his own, it muſt then be anothers transferr'd, tho' it ſtill inhere in him only, yet its value may be transferr'd to us: Thus Money may ſtill lye in its old Cheſts, and yet be transferr'd in accompts thorough twenty ſeveral Men, as in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and now in <hi>London</hi>'s Bank of <hi>England.</hi> Land is never remov'd from its place, and yet thoro' how many hands is it transferr'd, and its value is propos'd to be made as Current as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by ingenious men, and imputation is made uſe of to denote the way. The ſecond I ſhall not treat on, but I deſire that I may not be miſunderſtood, for it's not my Opinion that we are juſtified from Eternity, no, not until Faith. Juſtification preſuppoſes a righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a righteouſneſs that we have ſome relation in, which is by imputation made or founded.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is the common uſe of the word in Scripture, <hi>Philem.</hi> 18. <hi>If he hath wrong'd thee, or oweth thee, put that:</hi> The relative compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the antecedent, that Debt, that Injury, that Theft, <hi>on my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,</hi> impute it to me: The <hi>Levites</hi> are put in the room of the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, and the Heave-offering for the Corn of the Threſhing-floor. The three famous Imputations in Scripture are <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin to us, our ſin to Chriſt, and Chriſt's righteouſneſs to us: Our Faith and Religion are founded on them, and who denys one believes not aright any of them. The Imputation of our ſin to Chriſt is fairly ſet out in <hi>Lev.</hi> 16.21. <hi>Aaron</hi> ſhall put all the Iniquities, ſins and tranſgreſſions of the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon the head of the live Goat.</p>
            <p>I ſhall propoſe it thus, <hi>If our ſin be imputed to Chriſt, his righteouſneſs is to us; but our ſin is imputed to Chriſt,</hi> Ergo.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition is <hi>a Majore,</hi> for it's more credible that Priviledges be imputed than Penalties, a man may give of his own at pleaſure, but cannot puniſh another ſo: The aſſumption is expreſs'd in Scripture, <hi>The Lord hath laid on him the Iniquity of us all,</hi> Iſa. 53. 1 Pet. 2.24. Heb. 9. <hi>laſt.</hi> Pſal. 31.10. 40.12. 69.5. as he groan'd under our ſin, we may rejoice in his righteouſneſs. In 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. we have both Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, <hi>He hath made him to be ſin for us who knew no ſin, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him:</hi> The Queſtion is, Whether <hi>ſin</hi> or <hi>made</hi> be the words that are to bear the Interpretation? if <hi>ſin</hi> for <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> or <hi>made</hi> for <hi>imputed?</hi> I am for the latter: 1. Elſe ſin would be uſed equivocally in different ſenſes, and the Apoſtle would bring a So phiſm inſtead of an Argument; <hi>He knew no ſin properly,</hi> Ergo, <hi>made
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:200303:17"/>ſin;</hi> ſo he never knew any of his own, ours he knew. 2. Sin is in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to righteouſneſs; it is not meant the effects of righteouſneſs, a pardon; a pardon and righteouſneſs are not uſually put for one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 3. That righteouſneſs is ſtill imply'd to inhere in him: <hi>Of God in him;</hi> and indeed made a pardon is not good ſenſe. 4. <hi>Made</hi> is uſed for <hi>imputed,</hi> Rom. 5.19. <hi>By one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners, and by ones obedience many were made righteous.</hi> 5. <hi>Criticks</hi> diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſay, the latter is uſed for a Sacrifice, not the former; and I find this diſtinction made <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.2, 3, 4. <hi>Conſcience of ſin, remembrance of ſin, take away ſin,</hi> there is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; but <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>Burnt-offering and ſacrifice for ſin,</hi> there is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and I find it often in the ſeventy: Indeed the <hi>Hebrew</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth to ſin, and to expiate or purifie from ſin, but that is by an uſual rule in that language, for the ſame word to ſignifie contraries in different conjugations: I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd nigh twenty Inſtances in the Bible, the <hi>Greek</hi> doth not ſo. I ſhall add to this Argument this explication of it: (1.) Chriſt took on him the ſtate and condition of a guilty ſinner, he was in <hi>albo reorum,</hi> he was taken from priſon and judgment, he was in their ſordid form, and dead in Law, ſo the Believers are put in the condition and ſtate of righteous perſons, ſo treated. 2. He had on him the guilt of a Votee, that is, by his own conſent undertook to ſuffer; <hi>Lo I come,</hi> Pſal. 40. 3. Alſo the guilt of a Surety for his Votee's guilt, <hi>i. e.</hi> his own conſent put him in our place; a Votee's confinement and humiliation is for themſelves, not others; the Covenant of Redemption put him under the Covenant of Works, his own conſent brought him under the curſe, and our ſin brought us under; we enter by different doors, but come to the ſame place, the primitive Law. In oppoſition to this ſtands our freedom from that ſanction; the ſanction of that Law cannot touch a Believer, nor debar him from life, or any bleſſing God deſign'd him: Now all this guilt inheres in Chriſt, and this immunity and happy condition inheres in us: But, 4. <hi>Imputed</hi> ſpeaks a relation to what inheres not; there may be a juſt foundation of imputation in the imputers Goodneſs and Grace, a man may give to another in his book of Accompts as well as in his Will, and make the Title as ſure. 2. There may be an imputation when the ground of it is neither in the Imputer nor Imputee, as in the caſe of Bail, Surety or Hoſtages, who is may be kill'd, tormented for the treachery of his King, Countrey, or General; of this kind is the imputation of our ſin to Chriſt, and his righteouſneſs to us, it ſuppoſes them not to inhere; thus our ſins and iniquities are laid on him, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, and his Blood, his Death is imputed to us, his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; this Dr. <hi>Tuckney</hi> calls cogitative imputation.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:200303:18"/>
            <p n="3">3ly. The foundation this Tranſlation is founded on is a proof for it, and that is threefold: (1.) A contract between the Father and Son about it. (2.) An union. And, (3.) An office by vertue of that contract. In the contract theſe three ſteps ſeems diſtinguiſhable: <hi>Firſt,</hi> Chriſts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as God-man; it is not acording to the rules of Wiſdom, that the means ſhould be more noble than the end, and that this glorious perſon that is more excellent than Angels and Men, put them altogether, ſhould be meerly a mean, or a tool, (to ſpeak with reverence) to deliver us from miſery, and to make us happy; he would not in all things have the preheminence, if he were Mediator and the Means only, and we the end; the end is the moſt noble, the end is firſt deſign'd; he would not be the firſt born of every creature in the Womb of divine decrees, if his exiſtence was only thought on to ſave us: Nor could we be choſen in him, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5. If he had not ſome antecedent foundation in the thoughts of God, [compar'd with a conſulting deliberating man:] in order antecedent to our Election; the ground is preſuppos'd to the building: Let us then with the School-men conceive of ſuch a perſon, deſign'd of God as the laſt moſt perfect and glorious of all the Creation of God, one in whom God glorifies the fulneſs of his ſufficiency and bounty of his goodneſs to the uttermoſt, and he both by due and fitneſs becomes Lord and Governour of all the creatures. <hi>Secondly,</hi> To paſs the Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy of Angels above us, let us ſuppoſe by the conjunct Counſel of God the Father, and this now ſuppos'd <hi>Immanuel,</hi> [exiſting only in the divine nature, but a relative dignity and honour belonging to him as ſuch a perſon, and in ſuch an office, which was a glory, <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>Glorifie me with that glory which I had with thee, before the foundation of the World: viz.</hi> To be Lord and end of the Creatures is a great glory, all others being made for him, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. <hi>All things were created for him;</hi> but now as Mediator, and in a ſtate of humiliation, he is made a mean, and they the end] out of the ſpecies of men, ſome deſign'd and choſen to be the more immediate train and fellows of this great Lord, and end of all, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7. They are called Fellows; <hi>With the oyl of gladneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all thy Fellows:</hi> We may read the deſigns and contrivance in Chriſts interceſſion for the compleat execution, <hi>John</hi> 17.24. <hi>Father, I will that they alſo whom thou haſt given me be with me, where I am, that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold my glory which thou haſt given me:</hi> How they do it, we may read <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.11, 12. &amp;c. There being elect Angels as well as Men, renders this very conſiſtent antecedent to the fall. But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Theſe being in the loyns of <hi>Adam,</hi> and under the common Lot of Man as to their Creature ſtate, are permitted to fall with the whole maſs of humane nature: Elective Grace and Love ſhow'd it ſelf in their redemption,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:200303:18"/>but to Angels prevention, and their fall gives occaſion to a New Work and Office to this <hi>Immanuel,</hi> and New Diſcoveries of his Love and Grace to theſe elected fellows, <hi>John</hi> 12.24. <hi>Except a corn of wheat fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ground and dye, it abideth alone, but if it dye, it bringeth forth much fruit.</hi> He compares his death to ſeed; ſays he, if I dye not, I ſhall loſe all my fellows deſign'd; my Company and Train in heaven will not only be fewer, but I ſhall looſe one whole kind of them, and that of next kindred to my own nature; I will never ſuffer it, I have power over my own Life to lay it down, and take it up, I am reſolv'd to take their burden on my ſhoulders, the curſe they are under ſhall ſtrike thorough my Soul, but I will redeem them; I will give them a ſingular evidence of the goodneſs of their Lord and Maſter they are to ſerve. On the other hand, God the Father, with whom I ſhould have begun, the God of all Grace, that he might manifeſt it in all its variety, and render the difference between the Creature and Creator more luſtrious, and the degrees and ſteps of Happineſs more numerous and taſteful, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them, permitted them to fall, but knew of one among the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, a noble elect veſſel, that could not fall; yea, that could give ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for their tranſgreſſion; to glorifie his ſoveraignity, in ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what a ſubject was in his dominion, he commands him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. <hi>I come to do thy will; thy Law is within my heart;</hi> And to glorifie his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he gives this Lord of all to be their Prieſt, Sacrifice, Redeemer and Surety; the whole tranſaction we may read in the Covenant of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> Iſa. 50.20. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 89.3, 19, 20, 27. <hi>The Redeemer ſhall come to Zion, — This is my Covenant with them, my ſpirit that is upon thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall not depart from thy ſeed:</hi> It's a Covenant with him concerning them; <hi>I have made a covenant with my choſen, — one choſen out of the people, — I have laid help on one that is mighty: Zach.</hi> 6.13. A Counſel of peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Lord of Hoſts, and the man the branch. By vertue of this Covenant the Creditor may purſue him for his voluntary undertaking, and Chriſt may ſue out deliverance for his performance, therefore it becomes us to carry our petitions firſt to him, that in his right we may be delivered. 2. By vertue of this Covenant, and that relation that gave foundation to it, their ariſes a moſt ſtrict union between Chriſt and us: Now the more they are one, the more reaſon for his righteouſneſs to be imputed to us; they are one ſeed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16, 29. <hi>and to thy ſeed,</hi> which is Chriſt: You may purſue any of the Brothers that ſhare of the Fathers eſtate; any of the Members of the body may be puniſh'd for what another has done: We are all Members of one body. When a Society would give ſufficient ground of Credit, they put it in their conſtitution, that you may purſue one for all; here tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:200303:19"/>the oneneſs of nature all became Bankerupt thorough <hi>Adam;</hi> but much more united is that Society, one in Chriſt. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Ruther, par.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 251. (1.) One and the ſame legal party, the ſame object of juſtice; he that purſues the ſurety, purſues the Debtor: (2.) The Debt is one; It's but one Debt that Chriſt ſuffer'd for, and ſinners ſuffer for. (3.) The ſatisfaction or payment is one; it cannot be required of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal debtor, what the ſurety has paid. (4.) The acceptation is one, if he accept of payment from the Surety, he cannot purſue the Debtor; and the Diſcharge is one, as Chriſt was deliver'd for our Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, he roſe again for our Juſtification.</q> If a ſinner was aſſur'd that he were an elect veſſel, he might ſay, I have paid all in my ſurety; but as we have the priviledge of minors, ſo have we the folly, and therefore are treated as them, who have not wiſdom to manage their own Eſtate. 3. The Office that Chriſt was put in thorough this Covenant for us, is a juſt foundation for imputation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22. <hi>He was made ſurety of a better covenant:</hi> Whatever the word ſignifies there, it is for us as a Prieſt towards God, that he exerts it, as to the ſignification of the word tho' its but this once in the New-Teſtament, yet ſeveral times the ſeventy uſe it as the proper tranſlation of <hi>Gharab,</hi> which <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.1. and 17.19. ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth ſurety, ſo <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.9. <hi>I will be ſurety for him, let me bear the blame for ever:</hi> 44.32. <hi>Thy ſervant became ſurety for the lad:</hi> The end of ſurety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is to be a ground of Truſt; <hi>Dum curant homines ut diligentius ſibi cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſit, I have laid help on one that is mighty.</hi> (2.) One becomes ſo for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by contract, if in his own power, <hi>Fidejuſſor fit per ſtipulationem;</hi> be not thou one of them that ſtrike hands, or that are ſureties for Debts. (3.) It legally unites the perſons, <hi>Fidejuſſor, propriè dicitur debitor:</hi> He was made under the Law; <hi>Singuli in ſolidum tenentur;</hi> each are bound for the whole; <hi>He was made ſin, that knew no ſin.</hi> (4.) Tis of ſeveral kinds; either it may preceed or follow the Obligation, it may either be for debt or for perſons indemnity, or good behaviour, or for performance of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 36.8. <hi>Give pledges, I pray thee, to my Maſter, the King of Aſſyria:</hi> There is ſomething of each of theſe in Chriſts Suretiſhip; <hi>The Lord hath laid on him the iniquity of us all: Thoſe that thou gaveſt me I have kept: All that the Father giveth me, ſhall come to me:</hi> His Suretyſhip is that of ſatisfaction for guilt paſt, in the Covenant of Works, and that of caution in the Covenant of Grace: Thus <hi>Brinſley,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">Where there is a Suretyſhip, there is juſt ground for legal imputation, but Chriſts Mediatorial Office is a Suretyſhip, therefore it founds a juſt ground of imputation to them for whom 'twas undertaken.</q>
            </p>
            <p>There are two Queſtions, the ſolution whereof might contribute a conſiberable light in this affair, one is, What kind of righteouſneſs that is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:200303:19"/>which is imputed, and the ſecond is, how far it is made ours by impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and the one contributes light to the other, as to the (1.) There is righteouſneſs in Chriſt as he is God, his eſſential Holineſs. (2.) A Righteouſneſs as he is God-man, abſtractledy taken from the work of Redemption for us. (3.) There is a Righteouſneſs in his now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent glorified eſtate, wherein he applies what he did for us to us, which carries a conformity to the Covenant of Redemption, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is a righteouſneſs. (4.) There is a twofold righteouſneſs in his performance of the mediatorial office for us here below, one by reaſon of its conformity to the Mediatorial Law, which requir'd the faithful diſcharge of a King, Prieſt and Prophet, at his hand, the other in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Law that we were under, into which place that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking put him. As there are four kinds of righteouſneſs to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht in Chriſt, ſo there are three degrees of imputation; One is only for a perſons good Profit or Honour, and thus all in Chriſt is; 'tis an honour to mankind that there is ſuch a glorious perſon come of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, he is the light that enlightneth every one that comes into the world, he came to reſtore all things; that firſt relation I have before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned as head and end of all the Creatures, which fitted him, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd it proper and becoming that he ſhould become our redeemer, was much for man's profit and good: A 2d. Degree of imputation is for our ſake; <hi>for their ſakes do I ſanctifie my ſelf;</hi> when we become the end, and he the means, and thus the whole Mediatorial Office was undertaken by him, the whole of that work was the delivery of Mankind, eſpecially the elect, although we are not made Prieſt, Prophet and King, we reap the benefit of theſe offices, all their cauſality combined in our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and ſo doth his interceſſion unto this day: 3d. There is a near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er degree of imputation, when what's done is done in our name, room and place, which <hi>Brinſley</hi> calls the office of an Attorney: I ſhall give my thought of it by theſe two properties; When Chriſt doth for us what he was not obliged to do for himſelf as God-man. 2. When we who were oblig'd to do it, are freed from the obligation by his doing of't, and under this Chriſts paſſive righteouſneſs is comprehended; but paſſive righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs may juſtly comprehend the whole ſtate of his humiliation, from his Conception to his Reſurrection: He <hi>grew up as a root out of a dry ground, without form or comelineſs;</hi> he made himſelf of no reputation, and his firſt likeneſs to man was in the form of a Servant, and in that faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he became obedient unto death: Great glory and dignity was the due of the humane nature from the firſt minute of union. If a King ſhould marry the pooreſt Beggar, ſhe is Queen from that minute, and has a right to ſhare with her Husband in his plenty and honour, but a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:200303:20"/>deniedneſs to this, a being emptied of it, as 'tis in the 2d. of <hi>Phil.</hi> was a great part of Humiliation, and a birth of this kind was merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; the throwing ſuch a thick veil over his proper glory, the obſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his brightneſs by ſuch a thick cloud. All righteouſneſs has neceſſarily an active obedience accompanying it, or rather is it, for a paſſive ſuffering without it is not righteouſneſs; for all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs conſiſts in action and habit, and has a relation to the preceptive part of the Law, ſo what had been to us meerly a curſe, was to him obedience and righteouſneſs, becauſe he came under a Law to perform it; for what was the penalty of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s Law, was obedience to the Mediatorial Law, ſatisfaction to one, righteouſneſs to the other: (3.) Though Chriſt as man was bound to obey the Moral Law, <hi>viz.</hi> Not to bear falſe witneſs, not to ſteal or kill, yet his obedience was in ſuch circumſtances that rendered it meritorious; all his Sermons and his Death too was a bearing witneſs to the truth, and ſo an obedience to the ninth Command, yet not ſuch obedience as he was antecedently o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd to, his reſtoring that which he took not away, his being denied to that which was his due, was obedience he perform'd to the eighth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment: His praiſing God in the Church here below, his prayers and faith, with ſtrong cries and tears, was an obedience to the firſt table, that he was not oblig'd to as God-man: He might have been man without being the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and therefore he was not obliged to be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis'd, which was a great part of ſuffering, for 'twas a great diſhonour, an acknowledgment and publick confeſſion of Original Sin. And if our Original Sin thus on him, why not his Original Righteouſneſs, not as man, but as man in our likeneſs, born of a Woman, conceiv'd in a Womb, and <hi>Beza</hi> ſo expounds, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1, 2. <hi>Now there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, — For the law of the ſpirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, the unſpotted Purity and habitural righteouſneſs of Chriſt as man, being imputed to the Believer, <hi>hath made me free from the Law of ſin and death:</hi> That convinces of the one, and binds over to the other, <hi>viz.</hi> Death; thus <hi>Beza, Hemingius, Elton, Parr, Streſo, Downham:</hi> As he was the ſeed of the Woman, and our Brother, he was bound to obey the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law as ſuited to this eſtate, but there was not a neceſſity of being born of a Woman, he might have become man in a more glorious manner, he might have aſſumed ſuch a Manhood as he now wears; there is a great difference to be made between the dues of Chriſt as <hi>Emanuel,</hi> and as Mediator: The Originals are different, the one flows from his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Sufferings, Function and Inveſtiture, the other nakedly from the Union, which laſt remains, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. when the former is laid down. (4.) Though the Scriptures point at Chriſt's Death and Blood
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:200303:20"/>principally as the price and ſatisfaction, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. &amp; 5.9. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7. yet that may well be underſtood by way of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, it being the pinnacle of the penalty, and doth inſtruct us that the neceſſity of the ſatisfaction was founded in a holy, juſt and good Law, and not in the nature of God: The ſatisfaction did not make any change in the divine nature, to turn him out of an angry temper into a gracious, kind and merciful one, for the gift of the Son flow'd from the unchangeableneſs of his Love, but God as Supream King and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour by a juſt Law, well and wiſely eſtabliſh'd, could not in Honour ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Rebels to the Priviledges he deſign'd for them, without a ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made to the Government, which muſt be what the Law required, and that required Death; and as our Death begins with a mortal nature, and encreaſes thorough ſickneſs and weakneſs, until it be compleated in a Death-ſtroke, or ſome violence prevent the gradualneſs, ſo Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came like us in all things, excepting ſin; one drop of Chriſt's Blood, one day of his humility, had dignity enough in in it, but he was to pay what the Law required, and the Law obtained all its ends in him. This may help us to underſtand theſe Phraſes uſed very rudely, that God loves the elect when ſinning as well as when praying: Its true as he is God, for there is no change in him, but not true as our God or Governour, and the Language of Scripture is in this latter ſenſe, as he manifeſts himſelf thorough Law or Goſpel, theſe being Rules of his diſpenſations, and glaſſes of our knowledge. (5.) On the other hand, though we obey the Law in ſome meaſure, and have a meaſure of ſuffering, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God thorough Chriſt, if we have faith in him, yet this comes in as no ſatisfaction to that primitive Law, for we are not oblig'd to do what he did for us; it comes in as a preparing us for a poſſeſſion in a holy Society, where no unclean thing can enter, ſo the imputation of Chriſt's obedience takes not away the neceſſity of our obedience, more than his paſſive takes away the neceſſity of our ſuffering or dying; <hi>It's appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all once to dye,</hi> though Chriſt died, and its appointed for all to obey, though Chriſt obey'd; neither our ſuffering nor our obedience comes in as a part of that righteouſneſs that firſt Law requir'd of us, as belonging to the covenant of Works; the breaking of this clay veſſel ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Death, or what's equivalent, is neceſſary for our habitation in another Sphere, where this cannot enter; bleſſings of that would be a torment to this conſtitution: Sufferings are neceſſary to make us ſenſible what we deſerve, and what our Saviour ſuffer'd for us; Holineſs and Righteouſneſs is neceſſary by precept, and as a means to fit and prepare for that poſſeſſion. (3.) Thorough a congruity, as a fruit and an effect of that image of God begun to be drawn in us, by reaſon of which when
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:200303:21"/>in its perfection, it may be ſaid, <hi>The Law is not made for a righteous man;</hi> and we read of no Law given to <hi>Adam,</hi> but Ceremonial Laws; the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God is the firſt Law; the Moral Law reveal'd is but a Copy of that divine temper, and when its perfectly writ in a Man's Heart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any blot, miſtake or defect, to live holily is to live as he liſt, and by reaſon of this diſpoſition of Soul a Saint can never be ſaid to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out law, yet if we take law for an external Command, ſwaying by the force of its ſanction againſt the ſtream of Inclination, a man is neither of the Law, nor under the Law. The 2d. and laſt Head propos'd, was about the ſenſe of theſe words, <hi>Faith imputed to Righteouſneſs,</hi> about which there are theſe three Opinions: Some ſay that Faith is taken objectively, Faith comprehending Chriſt's Righteouſneſs is put for it, or Faith in juſtification is always valued as comprehending Chriſt's Righteouſneſs. 2. Others ſay that God out of his Gracious Acceptation takes faith for the Righteouſneſs Bleſſedneſs is due to; we ſay Chriſt's Righteouſneſs comes in the room of that, they that Chriſt merited, that faith ſhould be taken for it. The 3d. Which my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment embraces, is, that faith is reckon'd of God the mean of Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Inſtrument of conveyance of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to us: Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation applied to Faith is a note of Diſtinction, implying a double uſe of Faith, the one is by inheſion, and ſo it ſanctifies us, the other is by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and ſo it juſtifies us, becauſe it is the ceremony of Seiſin, by which we are inveſted with, and entitled to the righteouſneſs of Chriſt; this ſuits beſt with the former Metaphor of imputation in Books of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, for 'tis not only uſual and neceſſary to transfer and impute Eſtates in Books of Accompts, where great Funds and Banks are, but there is given to the perſon who is made Creditor a Bank-bill or Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, bearing the value of the transferr'd ſumm, ſo that bit of Stick or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per thorough imputation, if we compare it with theſe Bank-Books, makes the Man worth ſo much money as the transfer'd ſumm is; ſo in the Lamb's Book of Life there's not only a transferring of his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to us, but there is given out this Bill or Tally of Faith to us, by which we are entitled to it: There are many Arguments which may both prove and explain this. (1.) It is without doubt that all our priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are convey'd one way, Faith bears the ſame relation to them all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. It's ſaid the inheritance <hi>is of Faith, that it might be by grace;</hi> now <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Faith's</hi> call'd <hi>the ſubſtance of things hop'd for;</hi> Subſtance, ſaith <hi>Tho. Aquin.</hi> is the beginning of a thing that neceſſarily at laſt infers the whole, that's in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> an Earneſt; now if Faith be an earneſt of Heaven, it bears the like relation to other priviledges, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17. We read of a white ſtone, and in the ſtone a New Name; that was the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:200303:21"/>ſtone of abſolution, the Judge anciently inſtead of ſpeaking his Sentence convey'd it, by the giving of a white or black ſtone; ſo if Faith be the earneſt of our hopes, it's the ſtone of our pardon, it's the Ring of our Marriage with Chriſt, it's the Winte Raiment, Feaſt and New Name of our Manumiſſion by juſtification; out of Slaves we are made Freemen, and Faith is the mean and inſtrument of Inveſtiture with it. (2.) This ſence of it removes a conſiderable difficulty among Divines, the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, ſince Juſtification is a tranſitory act of God, and terminates upon the Creature, what it is that he doth when he juſtifies, or what bears the room of the juſtifying ſentence? moſt ſay, the Word of God, the Goſpel, but there's a great diſtinction between the voice of the Law and the voice of the Judge; the Law ſays, <hi>Whoſoever believes ſhall be juſtified,</hi> but the voice of the Judge is, thou <hi>John</hi> or <hi>Thomas</hi> art abſolv'd, its a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, poſitive and authorative Application of the Law. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> thinks, that God proclaims ſome publick Sentence among the Angels, but that's a groundleſs Notion; this ſeems to me moſt reaſonable, that the gift of Faith being ſuch a fruit of his ſpecial grace, that he gives to no ſinner but whom he juſtifies, its relative Language ſhould be, I juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thee, I pardon or abſolve thee, for the ſame Gift may have two Uſes, as a Ring in Marriage, it enriches and it marries, the one by its own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent value, the other by conſtitution; ſo Faith ſanctifies by its own inherent vertue, and juſtifies by impuration. (3.) It ſhews us what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the Holy Ghoſt has in our juſtification; all the three Perſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in all tranſient and external Acts, and in particular, this act is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crib'd to the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>But ye are waſh'd, but you are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd, but you are juſtifi'd in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God:</hi> There's no more reaſon for derogating juſtification from the Spirit of God, then from derogating ſanctification from the Name of the Lord Jeſus: The verſe contains two Bleſſings, Sanctification and Juſtification; two Authors of them, the Lord Jeſus and the Spirit; two ways of Application of their vertue, the Merit of the one, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Efficiency of the other, in name of the Lord Jeſus and by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God: Some think the Spirits Efficiency in Juſtification is to give the comfort and the knowledge of it, but that's no cauſality that may come forty years after the effect, but this gives an eaſie ſolution to the Text; the Spirit of God works Faith, which entitles to Chriſt's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, therefore we are juſtifi'd by the Spirit, and may be is called the Spirit of Adoption upon the ſame account, for the Spirit of Faith and Spirit of Prayer are one, and the Spirit of Adoption; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. is that whereby we call <hi>Abba,</hi> Father; ſo he may be alſo call'd the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Juſtification by his working, juſtifying faith, and this ſeems to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:200303:22"/>be pointed at 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.14. <hi>The grace of our Lord was exceeding abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, with faith and love:</hi> There are two Bleſſings mention'd, and both Preventive, <hi>exceeding grace, with faith and love:</hi> It is not ſaid, and Faith, and Love, to import barely the contemporarineſs of the Gift of Pardon and Faith, but the way of conveyance; thus God gave me Faith and Love, when I was a Blaſphemer, and a Perſecutor, and with Faith, or thorough Faith I obtain'd mercy, the Grace of our Lord was exceeding abundant in this bleſſing, in giving faith, and a pardon thorough faith. (4.) Chriſt's juſtification is a pattern of ours, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.24. <hi>He roſe again for our juſtification:</hi> 1 Tim. 3.16. He was <hi>juſtifi'd in the Spirit;</hi> the work of the Spirit in raiſing him from the Dead was a juſtifying act upon him; in the World he was condemn'd as a meer man, and thereby a deceiver, ſaying, he was God, but <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3. <hi>He was declar'd to be the Son of God with power, by the ſpirit of holineſs in his reſurrection:</hi> His ſtate of Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation was <hi>ſtatus reorum,</hi> he was in the condition of a guilty man, <hi>in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonand judgment,</hi> Iſa. 53. He was condemn'd, that he might condemn ſin in the fleſh, and that there might be no condemnation to them that are in him; he could not be puniſh'd under God's Government without ſin inherent or imputed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.8. <hi>He is near that juſtifieth me;</hi> he juſtified him in his raiſing him from the dead, and ſetting him at his right hand, ſo condemn'd him in humbling him; at the reſurrection his juſtification and vivification was one and the ſame thing in different relations, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. He was put to death in the fleſh, but quicken'd by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; when the Spirit quicken'd him, he juſtified him; his death was conſequently a condemnation, not only by man but God, as by his deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate counſel under his Government. <hi>Sydenham</hi> and <hi>Brinſley</hi> ſay, in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, as Attorney he took up the bond of the old Covenant in Court for his Clients, <hi>John</hi> 16. The ſpirit now in the Goſpel bears witneſs to his righteouſneſs as our Head and Surety, becauſe he goes to his Father, <hi>i. e.</hi> witneſſes he was juſtified as our Surety, and therefore his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is our acquittance or ſolution, he had never gone to Heaven elſe. (5.) No puniſhment can be juſtly removed before the Perſon be juſtifi'd or abſolv'd; the removal of our Spiritual Death by the gift of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is a removal of our greateſt puniſhment, therefore it carries abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in its boſome, and by it we may eaſily anſwer the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who argue our juſtification and ſanctification to be one, becauſe the Scripture mentions a relation certainly above a bare connexion of time, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1, &amp; 2. in <hi>v.</hi> 1. a connexion, but in <hi>v.</hi> 2. ſome cauſality. This place, ſays <hi>Stapleton, Ant.</hi> p. 625. is a torment to <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> but <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Comment frees himſelf, for though he yields inherent holineſs to be the ſenſe of the 2d. <hi>v.</hi> the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or for the influence it has on, no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:200303:22"/>in the <hi>v.</hi> 1. is thus, <hi>Non aſſignari caaſam à paulo, ſed modum quo ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimur à reatu,</hi> Sanctification contains a way of our being freed from guilt as well as filth of ſin. I argue againſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> thus, there could be no Argument to prove the one from the other, if both were one. 2ly. This interprets the relation, ſuch texts as this, and more evidently <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. implys between theſe two twins, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſame grace ſanctifies as a principle of efficiency in the Believer, and juſtifies as a foundation of relation it raiſes between the Believer and God, now let the <hi>Papiſts</hi> find one Scripture to torment a Proteſtant Interpreter with this key in his hand, or any advantage to their ſide who ſay juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is, juſtification is the ornamental or enriching value of the Ring, its marriage vertue? or the relation between man and wife? (6.) The being put in Covenant is alſo a relative bleſſing, and we are brought thereinto by God's pouring out his ſpirit on us; <hi>This is my covenant,</hi> Heb. 8. There is a very obvious objection againſt this, <hi>viz.</hi> The Scripture commonly attributes Juſtification and Pardon to the exerciſe of Faith, <hi>Abraham believ'd in God, and 'twas counted to him for righteouſneſs;</hi> but this Doctrine about it lays the ſtreſs of its juſtifying vertue on the gift of it, and the ſame objection may be otherways propos'd, the Scripture lays the juſtifying vertue of faith on the object of it, it is not a miraculous faith, believing I ſhall be cur'd, nor an Hiſtorical Faith, believing the truth of a particular relation in the Scripture, but a <hi>Believing on him that juſtifies the ungodly for juſtification, a believing on him that rais'd up Jeſus our Lord from the dead; thorough the belief of his being deliver'd for our offences, and rais'd again for our juſtification.</hi> And (3.) The like objections may be rais'd againſt theſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. <hi>That we are ſav'd by grace thorough faith, and that not of our ſelves,</hi> but as <hi>the gift of God: For we are his Workmanſhip,</hi> Tit. 3.5. <hi>Not by works of righteouſneſs which we have done, but according to his mercy he ſav'd us by the waſhing of regeneration, that being juſtified by his grace:</hi> Thus we ſee the Scripture lays an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> on each of them, the gift of Faith, the nature of Faith, the object of Faith, and indeed this Bill would be but a counterfeit one, if it wanted any of theſe Properties or Relations. 1. It muſt be receiv'd from him that hath the power, or elſe it is not valid; <hi>By his knowledge ſhall my righteous ſervant juſtifie many.</hi> 2. It muſt be in true form, rightly dictated, that is its nature, or not valid. 3. The divine conſtitution, the Law of Heaven has made it have ſuch a relation to Chriſt's righteouſneſs, the riches of his Grace, and the Wiſdom of the conſtitution ſhines in the fitneſs of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for our Souls are an open begging hand, a vaſt Appetite, <hi>It crys dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who will ſhew us any good?</hi> ſome good things I want, ſome more good, and this Faith claſps the hand on Chriſt offer'd, determines and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:200303:23"/>the deſire, as on an Object that has all fullneſs in him, full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o build a relation and union of right upon an union of nature; a Communion upon a cement of Union honours the Wiſdom of the contriver: So we ſee all theſe three muſt be in a valid Bank-bill; it is not worth a Farthing in it ſelf, a bit of Paper ink'd, but rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to ſuch a Summe, ſuppoſe 1000 <hi>l.</hi> it's worth ſo much, its very form conſiſts in relation to that ſumme, that's its Object, it ſignally bears it, and if rightly drawn, and receiv'd from the right owner, their Conſtitution and the Law will make me Poſſeſſor in due time: If any of theſe qualifications be wanting, it is not worth a Farthing: 1. Drawn in true forms. 2. Bearing relation to its proper Object. 3. Receiv'd from him who has the riches in his power to give: And I find our Catechim and Confeſſion inſiſts as much on this as any; <hi>Conf. c.</hi> 11. — <q rend="inline">Nor by imputing it ſelf the act of believing, or any other Evangelical Obedience, but by imputing the Obedience and Satiſfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſt unto them, they receiving it by Faith, which is the Gift of God. 11. Thus its the alone Inſtrument of Juſtification, <hi>i. e.</hi> they are not juſtified until the Holy Spirit doth in due time actually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Chriſt unto them. <hi>Our leſſer Catech. Q.</hi> How are we made partakers of the Redemption purchaſed by Chriſt? <hi>R.</hi> By the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual application of it to us by his Holy Spirit; for which they quote <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5, 6, 7. <hi>Q.</hi> How doth the Spirit apply the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c? R.</hi> By working Faith in us, and thereby uniting us to Chriſt in our effectual calling.</q> I may from thence form this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Maj. <hi>When Chriſt and his benefits are applyed to us, we are juſtified.</hi> Min. <hi>But when God effectually calls, Chriſt and his benefits are applyed to us.</hi> Erg. <hi>When effectually call'd, we are juſtified.</hi> It is granted, that Faith is the fruit of effectual Calling, and it cannot be deny'd that relations, <hi>viz.</hi> Juſtification, Adoption, flow as ſuddenly from their Foundations as effects can from their efficients. Or thus, Maj. <hi>The imputing Faith to Righteouſneſs is an application of Chriſt and his benefits:</hi> Min. <hi>But the Spirit by working Faith applys Chriſt and his benefits:</hi> Erg. <hi>The Spirit by working Faith imputes Faith to Righteouſneſs.</hi> But I need no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Teſtimony but Scripture, that way the Faith of Miracles tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſav'd, that way ſaving Faith juſtifies; but by the Spirits work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Faith of Miracles, <hi>when he ſaw their Faith,</hi> it was certainly a miraculous Gift, diſtinguiſhing and characterizing the perſons to be heal'd; to give him that Faith, was to ſay, thou art to live to be cured, there was no cooperation of the creature to a Miracle. Further, compare <hi>C.</hi> 4, &amp; 5. and we find imputing Faith to Righteouſneſs, and giving a Righteouſneſs, are the ſame; but Objections are not to be anſwer'd
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:200303:23"/>as Bullets in war, with the like, but explication and diſtinction: For the 1. The reaſon, the nature or exerciſe of faith is inſiſted on in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo much, is for our inſtruction; if the faith that God has given be that which entitles to Heaven and Happineſs. 2. The reaſon the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is ſo much intimated, is to prevent a moſt dangerous error that the World is moſt liable to, <hi>viz</hi> Leaning on our own righteouſneſs; ſuch fools, to take the Bill for the Summ: But its certain the owner and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietor muſt be the conveyer, I challenge to ſhow what he doth elſe that looks like it. For the 2d. I propoſe theſe two Diſtinctions: 1. Between the ſtate of juſtification and particular acts of pardon, or between the ſtate of adoption, and particular bleſſings in poſſeſſion; the former is convey'd thorough the gift of faith, the latter thorough the exerciſe of faith; a man gets right by the receiving of a Bill from the Proprietor, but when he comes for ſuch a part of it, he brings his Bill and ſhows it, and writes a receipt on the back of it. Tho' we are but once juſtified, we daily pray, <hi>Lord forgive my debts;</hi> and once adopted, we daily pray for more enjoyment of what is due to that title. 2ly. With Mr. <hi>Froſt,</hi> I propoſe a double inſtrumentality of Faith, one on the givers part, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the receivers; ſo it is with Bills too; the Proprietor conveys his right, and the Receiver afterward pleads his right; ſo it is with faith, God conveys Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs thorough it, and we plead for the benefit and uſe of it, as we need daily. But this I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that from the firſt gift of ſaving Faith, which turns us from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly to godly, we are juſtified and adopted perſons, which entirely throws out that legal conditionality that among <hi>Socinians</hi> has thrown out Chriſt's ſatisfaction, and among <hi>Arminians</hi> has impair'd and delay'd its vertue toward ſinners, until they come with ſomething in themſelves, a conformity to a new Law: And alſo <hi>Antinomianiſm,</hi> which is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination that comprehends all Errors, diſhonourable to the Law or Law giver, and whatever Doctrine is againſt the neceſſity, ſtability and perfection of the Law of God, is of this kind; whatever Doctrine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves the neceſſity of the Law, removes the neceſſity of Chriſt's ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and what Doctrine removes perfection from the Law of God, removes the Glory from God's Holineſs; but to ſuppoſe one under the Law ſav'd, and that Law neither fulfill'd nor ſatisfied by the perſonor his Surety, is to ſuppoſe the Law changeable, not neceſſary; if Chriſt only fulfill'd the mediatorial Law, and not that we were under, then that Law and Government bult on it was remov'd and chang'd without ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. If the grand influence of Chriſt's righteouſneſs by the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torial Law was to get it chang'd for an eaſier and leſs perfect, we muſt either ſay, the influence of Chriſt's ſatisfaction did terminate on the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:200303:24"/>of God, and make a change in his temper from anger to mercy, and perfection of holineſs to indulgence in carnality or ſay; that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son were of two different minds, but the latter thorough his obedience gain'd him to his mind; for what has influence on God, as Govenrour, has influence on the Law, (Adminiſtrations of Government muſt be rul'd by the Law) and what has influence on the Law for our good, muſt fulfill its precepts or ſatisfie its ſanction. The Law has no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Language, and if Chriſt did neither, the influence muſt not ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate on the Government, but on the nature God, or Fathers perſon in the Godhead. But the Scripture informs us, <hi>That God ſent his Son in the likeneſs of ſinful fleſh, that the righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfill'd in us:</hi> In us, ſays <hi>Vaſtius,</hi> by application, but in Chriſt by inheſion; in us by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, but in Chriſt perſonally, ſays <hi>Calvin, Muſcus, Beza, Rollock, Fulke, Cartwright, Elton;</hi> ſays Dr. <hi>Jacomb,</hi> all Proteſtants; he adds, his active and has paſſive as if they had obey'd it in their own Perſons, the Law is wholly fulfill'd in him, and that very righteouſneſs is ours in a Law ſenſe, and ſo fulfill'd in us. 3ly. It overthrows Libertiniſm, for if the ſame grace ſanctifies that juſtifies, they can never pretend to the one that want the other. 4ly. Popery, that makes juſtification and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification one, that differ as far as the Category of Quality and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I have no place for futher uſe, than to intreat every one as they love their own ſouls, and long for pardon of ſin, not to quench or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Holy Spirit of God, for that is his Errand as well as ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. 2. As ever they would enjoy this free ſpirit, be diligent and conſcientious in all Ordinances, that are miniſtrations of the Spirit; he is to be reciev'd in the bearing of Faith. 3. Study this imputed righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt, until thou experience moſt deep humility and moſt ſweet comfort from it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Thou ſtandeſt by faith, be not high minded, but fear;</hi> thou depends entirely for faith and righteouſneſs on another, thou waſt prevented in thy ungodlineſs, when thou receiv'd that gift. 2. How much will God do for thee, when thou art his Son and Servant, if he did ſo much for thee when an eremy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Much more then being now juſtified by his blood, we ſhall be ſav'd;</hi> thou haſt now gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to thee at once a perfect and an everlaſting righteouſneſs, a total forgiveneſs of all thy ſins, a work of holineſs God has engaged to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Grant me this, there was never any thing ſo well done by man, wherein there is not room for further induſtry,</p> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Calv.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:200303:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
